<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pietas Parisiensis, or, A short description of the pietie and charitie comonly [sic] exercised in Paris which represents in short, the pious practises of the whole Catholike Church / by Thomas Carre ...</title>
            <author>Carre, Thomas, 1599-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 127 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54913</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13197594</idno>
  <idno type="VID">98424</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240890770</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2273</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4309</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13197594</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54913)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98424)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 434:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pietas Parisiensis, or, A short description of the pietie and charitie comonly [sic] exercised in Paris which represents in short, the pious practises of the whole Catholike Church / by Thomas Carre ...</title>
                  <author>Carre, Thomas, 1599-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>252 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Vincent Du Moutier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Paris:</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First ed. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Catholics --  France --  Paris.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98424:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98424:1"/>
            <p>PIETAS PARISIENSIS OR A SHORT DESCRIPTION OF THE PIETIE AND CHARITIE COMONLY EXERCISED IN PARIS Which represents in short the pious practises of the whole Catholike CHVRCH.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS CARRE Confessour of Sion</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Euery Good tree yealdeth good fruites.</l>
               <l>And the euill tree yealdeth euill fruites.</l>
               <l>Therfor by their fruites you shall know them.</l>
            </lg>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
               <p>IHS</p>
            </figure>
            <p>PRINTED AT PARIS By VINCENT DV MOVTIER</p>
            <p>M. DC. LXVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98424:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98424:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS MVCH HON<seg rend="sup">D</seg> FRIEND W. D. ESQVIRE THESE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Vch Hon<seg rend="sup">d</seg> deare S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I had yours of the 20 of May in its due tyme: and noe sooner had I receiued it (such power of a commande haue your ciuile de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires ouer me) but I tooke pen in hand to returne you an answer which had bene longe agoe with you, had not my continuall infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie rendered me litle fitt for speedie complyance.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98424:3"/>
            <p>I am not without a deepe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentment, to obserue that you flill permitt inconsiderable doubts, cast in your way by I know not whom, retarde you from fixing vpon, what alone can make you eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally happie. You say in particular that you haue mett with so many loose and beastly cases among Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike authors, that you haue much adoe to beleeue that holinesse is practised, where so much licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciousnesse is taught. But I praye, are they taught in our councells? Doe you finde them in our Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls? Haue you heard them in our Pulpets? Meete you with them in our Catechismes? What are you startled at? If the braines of some few riotous children run ouer into extrauigances, must the good, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue their excesses pinned on
<pb facs="tcp:98424:3"/> her sleeue, while she neither teaches them, approues, nor conceales them? Nay while she expressly condemnes, and prohibites them with a heauie curse vpon them? Must the good wheate be reproued for á litte chaffe? Or Christs feild be disowned, because the enemye ouer sowed coc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le in it? This your ingenuitie will not iudge reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. And therfore, what I haue formerly said; (to witt, <hi>that san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie is a marke of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Romane church exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siuely to all other churches</hi>) I must still persiste in. Yes, she hath alwayes bene eminently knowne by that bage to all the world. She is holy in her heade Iesus Christ, who placed her vpon the rocke, and washed her in his owne pretious bloode: she is holy in that holy
<pb facs="tcp:98424:4"/> spirit who was sent to sanctifie her, and to teach her all truth: Holy in God the father, authour of all holynesse, to whom she is dedicated: Holy in all her doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, in her sacrifices, in her Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; in her discipline; in her pious members, á mongst whom there is neuer wanting numbers of persons famous for sanctifie. Holy in fine, in her continuall prayers to God, and charitable practises towards her poore neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Which two alone I will one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vrge at present, as being aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly satisfactorie, if compared to your cold practises, to make appeare where charitie is in her raigne, and consequently, where sanctitie is to be found, since it is indeede noe other thinge then cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Noe S. I neither know,
<pb facs="tcp:98424:4"/> nor seeke for, any other holinesse then charitie it selfe. It is that which is the end of the lawe; that the fulnesse of the lawe; that the lawe it selfe. <hi>Lex Dei cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas est,</hi> saith S. Augustine. The scripture commands nothing but charitie, nor reproues it anythin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge but cupiditie; and in these two it compriseth all Christian moralls. And as charitie is all, so all that it is conuersant about, is God and our neighbour; God, to loue him for his owne infinite goodnesse; and our selues, and neighbours, because it is his pleasure and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande. Obserue, I beseech you, in the ensuing discourse whether we or you make it more absolutly their businesse to comply with these two duties; and thence you will easily iudge on which side charitie,
<pb facs="tcp:98424:5"/> that is san<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctitie and holynesse resides: and at the same tyme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with S. Augustine, against your selfe indeede, but to your aduantage, that there can be noe charitie (that is sanctitie) among you, because you hate vnitie. <hi>Non habēt charitatem, qui Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siae non diligunt vnitatem.</hi> And againe, they haue noe charitie, who are cutt of from the communion of the Catholike church. <hi>Non habent charitatem qui ab Ecclesiae Catholicae com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munione praecisi sunt. de Bap. contra dona. l. 3. c.</hi> 16. Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cause, saithe he, in the same place it is the proper gifte of Catholike vnitie. Out of the Catholike com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie then noe vnitie: without vnitie, noe charitie, if charitie be wanting all things els profit not
<pb facs="tcp:98424:5"/> assures S. Paule. Cast your selfe then, deare S. into the bosome, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and vnion of the Catholike church, where charitie truly rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes, and where vnder her happie raigne, the least things profit to eternall life. Thither are you ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently inviteed. There, with open armes, are you cordially expected, by</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Hon S.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Iuly 20. 1666,</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your most humble aff. and best wishing seruant THOMAS CARRE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98424:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98424:6"/>
            <head>A SHORT DESCRITION OF THE PRESENT PETIE OF PARIS</head>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>THE FIRST ARTICLE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the glorie of God, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike church; the honour of that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble towne, where I had the happines to passe thirtie three yeares, the one halfe of my life, and to afford you full satisfaction, I will make Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris appeare the short mappe of the vaste Catholike world, and by that smale parte, giue
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98424:7"/> the idea of the whole.</p>
               <p>Pietie in generall, as S. Augustine tells vs, is the true worshippe of the true God, who, as he saith also, is not worshipped, saue one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by charitie. Now charitie has two respects, or chasty eyes two thinges alone, God incomparably aloue all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; and for him, our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as our selues. To des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe then the pietie of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, is noe other thinge then to declare what is practised there, in order to God and our neighbour, wherin the accomplishmēt of the whole lawe consists.</p>
               <p>And againe, as the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment of the lawe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists in two duties; so the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98424:7"/> therof may be reduced to two classes, the Pastours, and the people.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>Of the pietie, of the Priests and people in the daylie seruice of God. <hi>ARTICLE II.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO begin with the first, what may not be said with truth of the excellent Pastours of Paris, in otder to these two duties? They are all, generally, knowne to be men of exemplarie liues, and sound learning, being the most of them Bachelours, Licentiates or Doctours of the famous facultie of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne, Their places are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98424:8"/> to their merites, not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaced with moneys: and their whole endeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urs are imployed to sute their liues and actions to the dignitie of their places. They haue learnt of S. Gregorie, that Pastour of Pastours, in earth, vnder the souueraigne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stour Iesus Christ in Heauen, that <hi>the guidance of soules is the Arte of Artes.</hi> They know that their worke is not to saue their owne soules alone, but those of many, the highest thinge that man is capable of, being indeede the same for which the Almightie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, sent his onely sonne, as he also sent them with this minace, that if any of their flocke perish by their fault
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98424:8"/>
                  <hi>he will require his bloud at the hands ef the watch man.</hi> Hence it is, that they vse so diligent studie at the learned Sorbon, and els where. So many holy conferences (a blessed and common practise among the primitiue fathers of the wildernesse (<hi>vt in collationibus</hi> PP.) renewd in Paris among the clergie-men by good Mr Vincents Zeale, which they vse as well in in way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruatiue against the badd ayre of the world, to which they are still exposed by the necessitie of their function, as a most effectuall meanes to perfect them in their holy profession. The subiects of these conferences are alwayes some vertue or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98424:9"/> other. Wherin they treate of their nature, of their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar actes, of the motiues to acquire them, and the meanes to putt them in practise &amp;c. Togeither with the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their diuine state, as well in relation to God as their neighbour. Hence too are so many heauenly Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations vsed in their spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall retreates, (which is frequent among them) to fitt themselues to that sacred and dreadfull function. The lawe of God is the subject of these their Meditations, day and night, to begett worthy ād sublime thoughtes of God in their owne harts, to be conueyed afterwards into the harts of their hearers,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98424:9"/> hauing learnt of S. Augusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, <hi>that the truest begining of pietie, is to haue a most worthy esteeme of God;</hi> and of S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, that the true waye of a good Pastours proceedinge, is <hi>prius infundere quam effun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere,</hi> first to powre in, to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, then to powre out to others.</p>
               <p>They had reade in Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel, that it was the Pastours dutie <hi>to strengthen what was weake; to heale what was sicke, to binde vp what was broken; to bring againe what was cast away; seeke what was lost:</hi> and thence their whole studie is to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themselues skilfull phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions.</p>
               <p>They reflected of what they had heard from the great
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98424:10"/> Doctour of the Gentils, that they, as well as he, with due proportion, in qualitie of Christs Ministers, were to accomplishe, those thinges which want of the passions of Christ, in their flesh, for his bodie which is the Church; to witt, by applying the merits and medicinall grace purchaced by his payenfull passion, to the poore sinfull soules of their flocke, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riueing into them those foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of grace, conferred by their ministerie in the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of Baptisme, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the blessed Euchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste &amp;c. And they apprehend noe care and industrie of theirs sufficiently ans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to such high functions.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98424:10"/>
               <p>They called to mynd what the said S. Paule taught, and looked vpon it with a vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable astonishment <hi>euery high preist, saith he, taken from among men, is appointed for men, in those thinges which appartayne to God, that he may offerre gifts and sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices for sinnes, as well for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as also for himselfe.</hi> Hence numbers of priests, which the good Pastours take into their societies, and communities (some 40. or 50. some 100. some more, some fewer, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the vaste numbers of their Parishoners) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch daylie to the sacred Altars from morning till noone, with humble reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and veneration, to answere their peoples expectations
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98424:11"/> and deuotions, who concurre with them in a sweete harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, to offerre vp their vowes. If this true, cleane, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloudie sacryfice which the Prophete Malachye, foretold, be offered to God in euery place, from the rising of the sun to the going downe, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by the sacryfice of the lipps and hartes of the pious people, serue for the happie imploymēt of the whole fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, the afternoone wants not its part neither, which is daylie performed in the euensonge and compline, so that the church dores are as rarely shutt vp in Paris, all the weeke longe, as I haue rarely obserued them open in London, saue onely one day
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98424:11"/> in the weeke, as tho all the other dayes, they had noe God in england to be publik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly serued in their Parish churches. Besides these ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall pious practises of the people, which they exercise euery day in the weeke all Paris ouer, there is scarce one day in the yeare in which there is not some particular solemnitie, at one church, or monasterie or an other, to which there is great confluen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of people, by reason of some great preacher: or the exposition of the B. Sacramet, and pardons to be gayned (as it appeares by a certaine Almanacke made of sett pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to direct pious people to the said solemnities) and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98424:12"/> as there is noe day passes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out publicke seruice done to God; so there is noe houre of the day, or night, in which Gods prayses are not sunge in Paris (to say nothinge of what is done by the multitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of Catholike Christians in America, where our night is their day)</p>
               <p>The Oratorians begin the diuine office at 7. a cloke in the euening. At S. Geneuief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues at 8. The Penitents at 9. The Carmelites at 10. The Carthusians at 11. S. Victors our ladys and others till 2. From 2. till 4. at the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction Bernardines and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others. From 4. to 5. 6. and 7. at all Collegiall and Parish churches: so that what
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98424:12"/> the Royall Prophete foretold is perfectly accomplished: <hi>from the rysing of the sun to the setting of the same, Gods holy name is prayse worthy, praysed, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus is pietie practised all the worke dayes of the weeke all the yeare longe, to which on holy dayes is added a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and vpon sun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dayes, holy <note n="a" place="margin">The vse of holy bread will not be found to be any new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention of the late church of Rome howeuer tho it were so, yet more credit ought to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to it, then to all the Protestants op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions) but as ancient, at least, as Gr. Naz. Otation. 19, who saith, <hi>he was wont to blisse breade and signe it with the signe of the cross c.</hi> S. Aug. de peccatorum mer. &amp; remissione c. 26. and in manys other places, Paulinus Notanus ep. 1 ad seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum saying, <hi>that he changed breade</hi> in eulogiam <hi>into a blessed thinge.</hi>
                  </note> breade (which might passe for the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98424:13"/> sacrament in England, for any thinge I knowe, especially if receiued with faith) <note n="b" place="margin">Holy water Was in vse in the tyme of the Apostles, or at least soone after, since Pope Alexander, the fifth after S. Peter commands it in his first canonicall epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle As also Pope Damasus libro Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif c. 7. Epiphanius l. c. Tom. 2. contra Ebionitas. &amp;c.</note> holy water, <note n="c" place="margin">The vse of processions is as ancient, at least, as Tertullian in the seconde Age saying: <hi>let the Procession be modest,</hi> Praes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crip, contra Haere. c. 43, and l. 2, ad vxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. S. Amb. cōplaines that <hi>fewe came to the Procession</hi> S. Aug. l. 22. de Ciu. Dei c. 8. Tells how the people <hi>came runing to him,</hi> (to testifie the newes of a miracle done at S. Stephens shrine in the same church) <hi>where he satt being readie to goe in procession,</hi> as is practised all through the Cath▪ church till this tyme, euery sūday in the midst, or begining of masse</note> the procession and prone (that is a familiar ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication vpon the Gospell of the day) for the fore noone, togeither with a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98424:13"/> sermon and catechis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me for the afternoone. This is the ordinarie practise all Paris ouer. But the Pastours zeale for the instruction, and inflamation of the peoples hartes stayes not here, but further, by himselfe or his order, there are most elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent sermons made all the dayes of Aduent and lent, saue saterday, by the same preachers, who are followed with a wonderous concurse of Auditours, and a noe les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se admirably quiet attention of so great a multitude, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the least hemming or spitting, saue onely when the preacher makes his pawses to giue way to necessitie in that kind. Can then our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98424:14"/> without affected malice pretend that the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists are nousled vp in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which with the prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Manicheans they impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently obiect against them.</p>
               <p>But as the dignitie of preists and highth of pastorall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions is as venerable, as otherwise dreadfull, and brings with it according to Tertulians profound expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion <hi>intolerabilis magnitudo,</hi> a waight insupportable to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane shoulders; and as their practices are full of religion and pietie, so is their care as great, as farre as humanly can be deuised, to make a hopefull prouision of younge priestes to assiste them in their life tyme, and to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98424:14"/> in their places after their deathes. To this effect, a poore secular priest, but a great seruant of God, (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se admirable workes of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie haue made him famous all the world ouer, as here belowe we shall see) sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted an effectuall meanes to the most illustrious and most Reuerend Archebishope of Paris, then being (to witt aboue 30. yeares agoe) who highly approued and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it; and ordered it to be obserued by all that should pretend for holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders at his hands: and it is still continued by like ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, by his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, who doth now illustrate the said sea.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:98424:15"/>
               <head>The meanes suggested by that Holy priest to perfect the Priests. <hi>ARTICLE III.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THAT all that should take holy orders, should be obliged to make a spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall retreate at S. Lazares, where he gouerned, for the space of 10. days: that none should rashly intrude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues into so dreadfull a ministerie, nor take the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to himselfe, vnlesse called as Aaron. And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as this is a thinge, as worthy the approbation as imitation of all Bishoppes, I haue
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98424:15"/> thought it of vse, and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, to putt downe the exercises in that holy retreate in particular.</p>
               <p>Ten dayes then before the collation of holy orders, all the <hi>ordinandi</hi> repaire to S. Lazars, sometymes 50. or 60. sometymes to the number of one hundred, where they find bedd, and borde, and all thinges rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die by Gods prouidence, without their care or coste, and they are all most hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manely and charitably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, not so much into the house, as into the boso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the pious inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</p>
               <p>Two different intertayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are made to them
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98424:16"/> euery day. The one in the morneing, vpon the cheife heades of morall diuinitie: the other towards the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, of the vertues, and qualities proper to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended function.</p>
               <p>There are ten made in all of either kind.</p>
               <p>The first day they speake of the censures of the Church in generall.</p>
               <p>The seconde, of the said Censures in particular, as of excommunication, suspen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, interdicts, and irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie.</p>
               <p>The 3. day of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Pennance. As of its institution, forme, effects, and of the conditions neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie in the Confessiour.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98424:16"/>
               <p>The 4. Dispositions to the Sacrament of Pennance; to witt Contrition, Confession, and Satisfaction, with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences.</p>
               <p>The 5. Of diuine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Lawes: and of sinne in generall, with the diuision therof; the circumstances, the kinds, causes, effectes, degrees, and remedies.</p>
               <p>The 6. Of the three first commandements, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne mans dutie to God: and of three Theologicall Vertues, with the vertus of Religion, and its acts.</p>
               <p>The 7. Is an explication of the other 7. Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements which concerne our neighbour.</p>
               <p>In the 8. Of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98424:17"/> in generall, and of Confirmation and the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariste, in qualitie of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
               <p>The 9. Of the Eucharist as it is a sacrifice, and of Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me-Vnction, and Mariage.</p>
               <p>The 10. Is the explication of the Creede. With what is necessarie to be knowne by euery priest, and what they may teach the people thervpon with profit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>The afternoones incertaynement. <hi>ARTICLE IV.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE first day is of mentall prayer. First the motiues to it for cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giemen.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98424:17"/> 2. Wherin it consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes: 3. The methode and meanes to performe it. And in this they are exercised euery day for some tyme.</p>
               <p>The 2. Day the speach is of ones vocation, and of the state of a Church man. That this vocation should be had before one presents him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to Orders: wherin it consists, and which are the markes of it, with the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to know it, and to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>responde to it.</p>
               <p>The third speakes of the spirit of a clergieman: and shewes how he is to enter into this spirit: wherin it consists: the markes of it, the means to acquire it, and to growe perfect in it.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98424:18"/>
               <p>The 4. Treates of Orders in generall: of their institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, necessitie, matter, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, effects, and differences. With the dispositions ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie to receiue them.</p>
               <p>The 5. Of the first Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, with an explication of the doctrine of that cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie. The obligations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by it. The disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and qualities requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>The 6. a discours of the lesser orders in particular: their definition, the matter, forme, and functions, with the vertues required to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye with them worthily.</p>
               <p>The 7. Of the office of Subdeacon, and the vertues proper to this order, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98424:18"/> particularly of chastitie.</p>
               <p>The 8. Of the office of Deacon, and the vertues proper to it, particularly of charitie to our neighbour.</p>
               <p>The 9. Of preisthood, and of the knowledge necessarie for priests to acquitt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues of their dutie.</p>
               <p>In the 10. Is a discourse of the life of a clergie man. Wherin it is made appeare that they who haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued holy orders, ought to leade a much more holy life, then that of lay men, with many aduices to helpe towards such a life.</p>
               <p>All these thinges they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate in their conferences made afterwards, the better to committ them to memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98424:19"/>
               <p>They make euery day about halfe an houre of men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall prayer, and conferences vpon it afterwards, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct such as are lesse exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised therin. How to vse considerations, to moue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and to make reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions.</p>
               <p>They are daylie exercised in the functions of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which they are to take, and in the ceremonies of the holy Masse.</p>
               <p>They are made to recite the Office all togeither, and to obserue the stopps, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>They are disposed to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke their generall Confessions, at least from their last ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall one; and the next day they communicate at high Masse.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98424:19"/>
               <p>They haue 7. houres to repose in by night, and two houres of holy conuersation euery day, this is after di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and supper. In which tyme they reade the holy Scriptures, and Molina of the dignitie and sanctifie of preisthoode.</p>
               <p>Vpon sunday after they haue taken Orders, they assiste at high Masse, and communicate, in thankes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for their holy ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and so returne to their owne homes.</p>
               <p>Thus they are most sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantially and piously prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; which good dispositions are visibly obserued to be followed with fuch blessed effects, that huge benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98424:20"/> of admirable refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations in the whole Clergie of France, is seene euery where.</p>
               <p>I remember I haue fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently heard from the mouthe of that most Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious and venerable old Prelate Monseigneur of Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedoine (in whose blessed companie, I had the honour and happinesse to be for abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue 20. yeares togeither) who all that tyme, and before, was ordinarily imployed by the Archbishope of Paris to giue holy Orders, and the Sacrament of Confirmation; I heard, I say, from his mouthe, that the primitiue tymes seemed to him to be renewed againe in those ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98424:20"/> young men; who, said he (with much Emphasis his harte being dilated with ioy and iubilie) approched to me, as tho drunke with the newe wine of the Acts: so did the abundance of their hartes, breake out in sithes and sobbs, intercepting their words; and their ioyfull tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res forcibly burstforth, and watered my handes. This truth, which I often heard that Saintly Bishope powre out with so much feruour and high approbation, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowne to me, then to many others, I thought fitt to register downe, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and that holy institution.</p>
               <p>It this most happie Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98424:21"/> spreed its fruites all ouer France, and euen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend its, flowrishing branches into forraine nations too, as here after we shall see, how iust occasion doth it not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minister vs highly to extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le the pietie and charitie of the good tree whence they sprunge. We may well say of this holy Authour, what S. Henry spelman said in the begining of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells of one admired in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages: <hi>he was a starre of the first Magnitude,</hi> and euen indeede a prodigie of pietie. If I should vndertake to speake of the strength and puritie of his faith: the highth and confidence of his hope: and the euerburning flames
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98424:21"/> of his charitie, I should les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se want matter then tyme to deliuer it, and withall swarue from my designe, which is historically to offerre a smale scantling of a huge abundance; and not to fall into a panigerike which would find noe end. Noe, my ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me is not to prayse this saintly man, but God in him, since in deede the greatest Sainte is neuer praysed as he ought, but when we pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se God in the Sainte from whom all Sanctitie. Nor is it my meaning to prayse his vertues at home, in what euer degree of speculation or practise he might possesse them, but their profusion abrode vpon his neighbours,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98424:22"/> that credit may be still giuen to workes, not to words which are lyable to deceipt. All the prayse of vertue, can a pagan tell vs, consists in action; nor is vertue any orher thinge, as we are taught by a better Master, then <hi>the order of charitie.</hi> And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re was charitie euer better ordered, then where huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne respects had noe hand in the distribution, but it strea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med indifferently out vpon all, saue onely, where it found difference of necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and there it still most abounded.</p>
               <p>Nature, or prouidence, had sorted him out but a smale share in the goods of fortune, in his abiect extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98424:22"/> for he was wonte fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to tell the world, that he was but the sonne of a poore swinheard or cow heard The accession of Benefices added but litle to his wants, since he neuer possessed any but a poore Cure, and that for a smale tyme. And as prouidence had begun with him, so he went on with her, making pouertie his portion by his free choyce; and the companie, and care of the poore, his center all his life longe; and himselfe, and all his, their stewards.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:98424:23"/>
               <head>Of the begining, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners of the Congregation of the Mission, and Missioners which complyed with the care of this stewardshippe. <hi>ARTICLE V.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the yeare of our Lord 1624. March the first, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun the happie establishment of the companie of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the priests of the Mission, in the Colledge of <hi>Bons enfans</hi> conferred vpon M. Vincent Paule, by the most illustrious Iohn Francis de Gondy Archbishope of Paris, to that purpose. To witt, his brother the Generall of the Galeeres, and his most
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98424:23"/> vertuous lady, being well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted what great thinges Mr Vincent had performed in diuers of their owne Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, in that kind, for the good of their poore vassalls, and Gods glorie, they had longe conceiued a pious desire to concurre ioyntly to be Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the said Mission, which they imparted to their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Archbishope, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vse of his power ouer Mr Vincents spirit (whom they knew to be as slowe in vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, as diligent and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in performing what he once vndertooke) to induce him to accept the charge. Which was done accordingly, and he wholie acquieseed to the Archbishops pleasure.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98424:24"/> Here vpon was 40000. liures tournois, or 4000. pistolls putt downe by the most no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pious founders in Mr Vincents hands, in readie money. Vpon the following conditions.</p>
               <p>First, that the end and whole imployement of these Missio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries should be, to tend to, and to procure the corporall and spirituall good of the poore people of the villages; and that too so wholy, that they were not to meddle to preach or administer facra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in any considerable townes, saue in case of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame necessitie, but to goe from village to village to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct and assiste those poore abandoned soules. Secondly
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98424:24"/> that they were to renounce all church Benefices, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and offices, to applie themselues intirely and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely, with the leaue of the ordinaries, to the saueing of those poore people, by ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, catechismes, generall confessions &amp;c. And that too at their cost and charges, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out admitting of any retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution or rewarde, in what kind soeuer.</p>
               <p>Thirdly that the election of proper subiects should be at Mr Vincents pleasure, who should gouerne them all his life longe.</p>
               <p>And that which is worthy of speciall obseruation, is, that these blessed Founders, so purely and disintressedly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98424:25"/> aymed at Gods glorie, and the good of the poore alone, that they made noe reserues, of any fixed thinge relating to themselues in particular; either in point of honour or profit. In so much, that they imposed noe obligation of masses or other prayers, either in their life tyme, or after their death, saue onely the right of Patronage accorded by the holy canons of the church, part of which also they renounced, as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination to offices &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:98424:25"/>
               <head>Mr Vincents complying with the Foundation: and of the establis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hment of the Mission in diuers places. <hi>ARTICLE II.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WITH this vertuous foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation Mr Vincent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to complie, hauing one onely companion in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining, which soone after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased to the number of 10. or 12. and ere this, as we may guesse with probabilitie, mounts euen to thousands. Here vpon me thinkes a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable doubt might be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, whether as there was neuer holy worke begun, with lesse of man, and more of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98424:26"/> God in it, so there were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any which God more owned, and bestowed a larger benediction of successe vpon, euen within the compasse of his life tyme who begun it. For in a short tyme he sawe his children as young plants of oliue trees, in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, round about his table, and the oyle of heauenly graces streaming downe in great aboundance vpon that venerable ancient heade, it thence plentifully ran downe euen to the hemme of his garments. Hence it was that from that riche sourse whole colonies did spreedd themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues not onely all France ouer, but euen extended themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to forraine Lands.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:98424:26"/>
               <p>The first establishment flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing from this fountaine, was begun at Toul in the yeare 1635. by the consent and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Bishope of the place.</p>
               <p>The seconde at Richlieu 1638. founded by the most Eminent Cardinal of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, with obligation to preach &amp;c according to their pious institute, to the poore of the Diocese of Poitiers, as also to those of Lucon of which he had formerly bene Bishope.</p>
               <p>The third was founded by the said Cardinall at Lucon it selfe in the yeare 1645. with full power granted by the Bishope therof to preach, and teach &amp;c. all ouer his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cese.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:98424:27"/>
               <p>The fourth at Troye, in the yeare 1638. by the charitable assistance of the Bishope of the place.</p>
               <p>The fifth in the Diocese of Geneua in the yeare 1640. where the Commandour of Sillery founded them a semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie where they still labour with much fruite. Still with the approbation of the Bisho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of the Diocese which I shall not herafter neede to mention.</p>
               <p>The Sixth in the yeare 1641 at Rome, by the Duchesse of Aiguillon, who also foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded seauen of the said Missio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries in her duchie of Ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guillon. The eight was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againe by the said Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chesse at Marceilles: The
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98424:27"/> nighth in the Diocese of Caors in the yeare 1643. by the saintly Bishope therof. The tenth in the Diocese of Reimes by the Archbishope Vallancy 1644. The 11. at Montmirail in Brye by the Duke of Rets in the yeare 1644. The 12. at Zaintes by the Bishope and clergie the the same yeare. The 13. at Mans by the Bishope 1645. The 14. in the Diocese of S. Malo at S. Meen in the yeare 1645. The 15. at Genne in Italie at the instance of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall Durasso, Archbishope of the said place, in the yeare 1645. The 16. at Agen by the Bishope of the place 1650</p>
               <p>The 17. at Crecy in the Diocese of Meaux in the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98424:28"/> yeare 1641.</p>
               <p>The 18. was founded at Vaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia in Polognia by the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of that most pious Queene, in the yeare 1651.</p>
               <p>The 19. in the Diocese of Montauban by the Bishope of the place. In the yeare 1652.</p>
               <p>The 20. At Treguier in Britanie by the. Bishope and count of the place. In the yeare 1654.</p>
               <p>The 21. at Adge in Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc by the Bishope and Count of the place in the yeare 1654.</p>
               <p>The 22. at Turin in Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont at the instance of Mr le Marquis of Pianezze who founded them. 1654.</p>
               <p>The 23. at Amiens by the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98424:28"/> Bishope of the place, with the perpetuall direction of his seminarie.</p>
               <p>The 24. At Noyon by the Bishope of the place, with the direction of his seminarie; This was resolued vpon in Mr Vincents life tyme, but was onely accomplished after his death.</p>
               <p>He sent also Missionaries into Africke to Tunis and Argers to ayde, instructe, and comfort the poore Christian slaues, who were there to the number of twentie or thirtie thousand. To Madagascar also beyond the lyne, a voyage of sixe monthes sayle, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour the conuersion of those poore infideles, Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Hebrides in the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98424:29"/> furdest partes of scotland, and into Ireland. O strange be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction vpon the pious la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of one poore preist! of him certainly may that of Ecclesiasticus be verified: blessed is the man who is without spott, and that hath not gone after gold, nor ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the heapes of money. Who is this, and we will payse him, for he hath done meruelous thinges in his life. Meruelous thinges indeede, and such as might hardly gayne credit, were not all Paris a witnesse therof, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it was generally knowne that he was a person of so litle selfe interest that many had shewne themselues more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to offerre great aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98424:29"/> then he to admitt of them. So that of him might truly be said, that hauing nothing he possessed all: to witt the noblest harts of Paris ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heared to his pious counsells, and their purses lay open to his charitable suggestions.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the huge assistance, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities which Mr Vincent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to be sent to Loraine.</head>
                  <p>HEMCE it is that in the extreame wants and ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lamities of Loraine, though otherwise an enemye coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, he procured to be sent thither at diuerse tymes, and caused it to be distributed amongst the most needie, by
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98424:30"/> his Missionaries, to the sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of sixteene hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand frankes (that is 1600. thousand pistolls) to which the said Missionaries added noe lesse large proportion of their sollicitudes and paines, who spent their whole tyme for many yeares togeither in visiting the poore and the sicke, and in fournishing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousands of them with all things necessarie for body and soule. All these thinges might haue bene more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and authentically testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the persons relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by those charities, had not humble Vincents care to staue off vanitie vpon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, preuented the same:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98424:30"/> for wheras one of his, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the distribution, offered to send publicke at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation of his, and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes fidelitie therin, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued answer from his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest father <hi>that he would not haue him to demande any such testimonies, it being sufficient that God knew their workes, and that the poore were assisted, without producing any such attestations,</hi> these were his words. Yet his prouidence who will haue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to follow those that flye it, and will exalt him who humbles himselfe, fayled not to drawe diuers authenticall testimonies from the grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hartes of the oblidged persons addressed to him, nor shall they lye in obscuritie
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98424:31"/> but shall be placed in the light, to Gods honour in him, and an admirable example to others, accordinge to that Euangelicall maxime: <hi>so let your light shine before men, that they see your good workes, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie your father who is in heauen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I. Iohn Midot Doctour of diuinitie, Archdeacon, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and Vicare Generall of Tou the sea being vacant, doe certifie and atteste, that the preists of the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Mission, who resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in this towne, continue any tyme these two yeares, to comfort, to cloth, to feede, and giue physicke to the poore, with much edification and charitie. First of all, they haue taken into their owne
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98424:31"/> house a matter of sixtie sicke persons; and haue lodged about 20. more in the suburbs. Secondly they giue almes to a number of other bashfull poore reduced to extreame necessitie, who betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues hither for refuge. Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlie they receiue a many poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re naked and lame soldiers which returne from the kings armie into their owne house, and cure. In which charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble actions, and other their pious comportments, all good people are wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully edified. In witnesse wherof I haue signed and sealed these presents. Toul Decemb. 1639.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:98424:32"/>
                  <head>The copie of another letter.</head>
                  <p>S<seg rend="sup">R</seg>. since a great many yeares that this poore towne hath bene afflicted with plague, warre, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; which hath reduced it to this excesse of miserie wherin now it is, in lieu of consolations, we haue onely mett with rigourous dealings from our creditours, cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie from the soldiers, who forceably robbed vs of the smale quantitie of bread which we had: so that it seemed that the heauens had nothing but rigours for vs, when behold one of your children in Iesus Christ, came loaden with almes, which
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98424:32"/> hugely tempered the excesse of our miserie; and raysed our hopes in Gods mercy. Sr. since our offences haue prouoked his wroth, we humbly kisse the hand which doth punish them, as we also receiue the effects of his diuine mercy, with the resentements of an extraordinarie acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. We blesse the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his infinite clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as well these who relieue vs with these seasonable cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as those who procure them and distribute them amongst vs; and you in particular, deare Sr. whom we looke vpon, after God, as the principall authour of so singular a blessing. To tell you how well it is applyed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98424:33"/> to this poore place, where the cheife persons are redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to nothing, the Missona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries you haue sent, will relate it with lesse interest then our selues. They haue bene eye witnesses of desolation, and you will find in the sight of God the eternall obligations we owe you, for haueing succoured vs in this our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable condition.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>From the officiers and councell of Luneuille 1642.</head>
                  <head type="sub">A Copie of another letter.</head>
                  <p>S<seg rend="sup">R</seg>. you haue so singularly oblidged vs, in the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance you haue afforded to our poore begges, to our
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98424:33"/> bashfull indigent, and to our sicke persons; and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to our religious houses, that we should proue vngratfull if we deferred any longer to testifie our sensible acknowledgements, we being able to assure you, that the charities which you haue sent hither, could neuer be better distributed and imployed then vpon our poore people, who are verie many in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and specially vpon the religious women, who are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute of all humane assistan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce; some of them not inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any part of their smale reuenues euer since the warrs; and others not receiuing any thinge from the richer sorte of the towne, who formely
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98424:34"/> gaue them almes, they, being now, depriued of their owne meanes. Whence we find our selues oblidged humbly to beseech you, deare Sr. as by the presents we doe, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the same charitable assistances, as well to the poore, as to the Monasteries of this place, which hitherto you haue done. It is a subiect of great merite, for those that doe these good workes, and for you who haue the conduct therof, which you performe with so much pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and dexteritie, to the gayning a great crowne in heauen.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>From the Magistrates of Mets</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Octob. 1664.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="article">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:98424:34"/>
               <head>Informations of the calamitous state of Lorraine sent to Mr Vincent by some of his Misso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries. <hi>ARTICLE VIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEING arriued at S. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel I find so great a number of poore people, that I am not able to giue to all; there are aboue 3. hundred in verie great necessitie, and 300. more reduced to ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treamitie. Sr. I tell you noe more then a bare truth; there are aboue 100. of them, who appeare onely squelletes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with skinne, and are so
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98424:35"/> gastlie, that vnlesse God did strengthen me, I should euen dreade to looke vpon them. Their skinns are like taunie marble, and are so dried vp, that their teeth seeme to be drye and discouered &amp;c. At our last distribution of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de there were 1052. poore people, besides the sicke who are in greate numbers, which we assiste with foode, and conuenient medicines &amp;c. O Sr. what a number of soules goe to heauen through pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie! since I came first into Loraine, I haue assisted aboue a thousand poore people at their death, who shewed all of them, that they were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly well disposed to dye &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:98424:35"/>
               <p>In fin to contract much into a litle (for should we insiste vpon particulars we should neuer make an end) we may say with truth (to Gods honour and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable pietie of Paris, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of the Dames of the charitie) that the profuse li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralities procured by this saintly priest, were extended by his wise care in the distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting therof, to the releeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of 25. townes, to say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge of many bourges and villages. O blessed and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable example of Parisian charitie, neuer happly to be parelled by any other place in Christendome? O incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable power of the riche pouertie of one poore priest,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98424:36"/> who was able piously to picke the purses of thousands of rich people. May his fruitfull pouertie, and their plentifull possessions and posteritie be blessed for euer and euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="article">
               <head>Of assistance giuen in Paris, to many of the nobilitie of Lorraine <hi>ARTICLE IX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MVCH was done, but here was yet noe end: for the poore ruinated nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the same countrie, hauing obserued how sweetly and comfortably the streames of Paris pietie had flowed vpon the poore of their land, while bashfulnesse permitted
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98424:36"/> them to taste noe parte in the same, howeuer their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie in verie deede was so much more sensible, by how much they had bene lesse acquainted with want, and found it lesse sutable to their condition, the sense of their miserie taught them to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise a lesson which they had neuer learnt, so that they tooke courage to run vp to the fountaines heade, and cast themselues into the open bosome of that comon father of the poore Mr Vincent, who tooke their miserie to harte, by commiseration, and his charitie wanted not an inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to relieue them; not now by the ladys of the charitie whom he still reserued for a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98424:37"/> greater imployement, but by certaine men of knowne pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and charitie, who had mettings at S. Lazars euerie month to taxe themselues to a certaine summe which might reach to the subsistan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of that poore nobilitie, which was caried to their respectiue chambers by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of honour, euery month for 7. or 8. yeares space; till their countrie at length be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be in a better condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at which tyme too Mr Vincent fayled not to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish them with moneys to returne home, and to afford them a liuelihoode for some tyme after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="article">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:98424:37"/>
               <head>Of the releife procured by the same meanes for Picardie and Champine. <hi>ARTICLE X.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRVE charitie neuer meetes with a <hi>non plus vltra:</hi> by how much more she giues, by so much more she increases: for the purchace of it, should a man giue all his substance, he would esteeme it as nothinge. One would haue bene apt to haue conceiued, that this poore priest had performed his part to the full, and that the large distributions made to Lorai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, might well nigh haue
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98424:38"/> drayned the purses of Paris: but charitie which hopeth all things, is neuer idle, neuer wearie, neuer with out coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, neuer without inuention; where so euer she meetes with equall necessitie, she finds in her harte equall compassion, which dilates it to an answerable liberalitie. What had Mr Vincent then to doe but to season the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hartes of the good ladyes of the charitie, and other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous persons with the crying calamities and miseries of their neerer neighbours of Picardie and Champine? And how could he doe this with more credit, and effect, then by the fresh informations of his pious Missionaries who
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98424:38"/> were labouring in the middst of desolations? His pious Dames he assembles once or twice a weeke to this purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se. Reades to them what he had receiued. There are aboundance (writes one) who are afflicted with fluxes and feeuers; others are cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered with scabbs, and purple-spotts, tumours and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stumes. Many there are swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, some in their head, some in their bellie, and some againe all their bodie ouer. These infirmities were cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by eating wild rootes und bread of branne which a dogge would hardly eate. Our eares are filled with pittifull lamentations, and outcryes for breade, and how
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98424:39"/> soeuer sicke they are, they dragge themselues through rayne and mire two or three legues off to haue a few pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Many dye without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession and the other sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and euen buriall it selfe, the poore dead body being left in their homly cottages till they are eaten vp with wildebeasts. Another writes thus, we are newly returned from visiting 35. villages in the deanerie of Guife, where we found neere vpon 500. people so excessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely miserable, that they seaze vpon deade dogges and horses, which are the wolues leauings. And in the verie towne of Guise, there are aboue 500. sicke persons, who
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98424:39"/> are lodged in caues and dens. Some of them haue eaten noe bread in 6. or 7. dayes, not so much as that which they make of barley branne, which is kept for those which are most at their ease. Their meate is lezards, frogges and wild herbes. This litle, of the longe relations, of miseries yet more horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, both for soule and bodie, issuing from the mouth of that pious priest, who gaue life and energie to all that he pronunced, had presently reached the compassionate bowells of those charitable Ladys, who presently vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke the releife of those two provinces, and once againe illustrated the pietie and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98424:40"/> of Paris. All things were wantinge to those poore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandonned persons in the ruinated countrie. And a prouision of all thinges was also presently made at Paris necessarie for body and sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le. And that too in such abundance; that the chambers and cabinets of most illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious Duchesses and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quesses and other great La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dys, might seeme to be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the Magazins of Marchants, or Apothecaries shopps; such a number of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of apparell, shirts, smoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, shoes, stockins, couer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, sheetes, and other linen necessarie for the sicke, as also drogues for physicke confeictures &amp;c. Togeither
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:98424:40"/> with chalices and other orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the church &amp;c. which togeither with corne to sowe the neglected feilds which lay fallow, and what was sent in drye money, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted in all to fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousand frankes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king halse a french million, to the eternall prayse of the charitie of Paris be it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <head>The establishement of an Hospi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall in S. Lazars suburbs for the children found exposed in the streetes. <hi>ARTICLE XI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHILE Mr Vincents and the pious Parisian ladys
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:98424:41"/> charities, had wrought and were still working, such won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders amongst the poore dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed people abroade, his pious care did not, the while, ouerlooke Paris, and was wanting at home. For though he well knew that our dutie of louing our neighbour ought to be extended all the world ouer, since as S. Augustine saith, <hi>omnis homo homini proximus,</hi> that euery man is neighbour to each other: yet he knew also that there is an order in charitie, wherby we are bound to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye the cheife part of our care vpon our neerest rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whether for bloude, place, or dependance: when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that of S. Paule: <hi>if any</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:98424:41"/>
                  <hi>man haue not care of his owne, especially of his domesticalls &amp;c. he is worse then an infidele.</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce it was that his eyes were fixed, and his wounded harte was bleeding vpon the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable condition of poore abandonned new borne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, whose bodies and sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les are exposed to vtter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, either by the vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall crueltie of naughtie women, or by the extreame pouertie of necessitous pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who couertly leaue them in the streetes at all aduentures. Of such kinde of deserted innocents it is obserued in this vaste world of Paris, that scarce a yeare passes without three or foure hundred in the towne and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98424:42"/> suburbs. Such agrowing nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie euery one will iudge cannot be maintayned with a litte. And indeede the annuall maintenance therof mounts to noe lesse then 4000. pistolls. A large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion truly, which is still growing vp to more and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, <hi>sed charitas nunquam excidit</hi> charitie too growes still and, knowes noe bounds, and she is fournished with a skilfull Aduocate to pleade her pious cause, whose charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble harte seemed to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually breading with S. Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, his Patrone, and to say with Rachel, giue me (these) children otherwise I shall dye. And so addressing him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe to the good Ladyes,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98424:42"/> vseth this plea with a voyce lowder then ordinarie, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated with his wonted zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le. Ladys, saith he, compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and charitie haue moued you to adopte these poore litle creatures to be your children, you haue hitherto bene their mot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge to grace, euer since their mothers, according to nature, abandoned them. Leaue for a while to be their mothers, to become their iudges. Their life and death are in your hands. I am readie to take your votes, it is tyme to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their sentence; and to know whether you will not any longer take pittie of them. If you continue your charitable care towards them,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:98424:43"/> they liue: if not, but that you will abandonne them, they infallibly perish and dye, as your owne experience putts you out of doubt. Noe sooner was this said, but the tender harted ladys found themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues so strucke with the ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of his speach, that they all vnanimously resolued, that cost what it would, they would not quitt this charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble interprise. Nor did they; for those poore soules are till this day nourished and brought vp under the care and assistance of ten or 12. good sisters of the charitie, with the helpe of a number of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouses who liue in the said Hospitall, togeither with a many more in the countrie
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98424:43"/> who receiue a monthly pay. When they are once wayned, they are deliuered backe to the sisters of the charitie, who in teac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inge them to speake, teach them also to pray, to know God, to loue and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue him. As they grow vp in yeares, they are taught some litle workes to keepe them out of idlenesse, till proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence sorte them with some sitt occasion for their future beeing. Of these poore soules may be truly said, they had perished, if they had not so perished, since they fell out the vnworthy hands of step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers, into mothers ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hands, nay euen into his who saith: hardy is it credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that a mother should
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98424:44"/> forgett the fruite of her wombe, yet should she doe it, I will not forgett you saith our heauenly forter father.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="article">
               <head>Of the establis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ement of the Dames and sisters of the charitie in Paris and elswhere. <hi>ARTICLE XII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE whole lawe and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes saith S. August. after his master S. Paule, are nothinge els but loue, whence he feares not to say, <hi>ama &amp; fac quod vis.</hi> Nor doth any endeuours of man so infally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly euince our loue to God, as the loue we shew to our neighbour: whence the same
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:98424:44"/> same S. August saith: beleeue it, you neuer walke in a more secure pathe towards the loue of God, then by the charitie of man to man. This certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he had redd in S. Ihon, that louing Apostle, saying: if any man shall say, that he loues God, and yet hateth his brother, he is a lier, for he that loueth not his brother whom he seeth, how can he loue God whom he seeth not! And if our loue to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in generall be a certaine conuictiō of our loue to God, how much more absolutly doth it appeare, in applying our charitie to those neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, who haue nothing hamanly speaking, to gaine, our affection or assistance to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98424:45"/> to them, tho they are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise more particularly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to vs by our deare Lord and master then all others. He hath left them to be his receiuers of our cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable contributions to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe in their persons, <hi>what you giue to those least ones of myne you giue to me.</hi> Nay more he hath left himselfe in them, to be fedd, to be clade, to be lodged, to be visited by vs. We haue noe lesse then his diuine word for it: I was hungerie, and you gaue me to drinke: I was a stranger and you receiued me; naked, and you couered me; sicke and you visited me &amp;c. How could he euer, cryes out S. Cyprian (<hi>and</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:98424:45"/> we with him) haue more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly prouoked vs to the workes of iustice and mercy; then in declaring that is giuen to himselfe, which is giuen to the poore and needie? To thend that they, in the church who are not moued with res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to their brother, may at least be moued in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of Christ: and that they who doe not consider their fellow seruant in his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie and want, may not fayle to reflect, that their Lord and master is represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that verie person whom they despise. This reflection was deeply ingrauen in Mr Vincents harte, as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in all his actions, yet more particularly (were it
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98424:46"/> possible) in this which we are about to relate. There appeared nothing of splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour or magnificence in this businesse, but contrarily an absolute contempt of it, and an effectuall meanes to make maginficence, and wordly greatnesse, stoope to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test miserie that haply euer heauen beheld; and therby to leaue to the world the most admirable, and amiable exā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Christian humilitie, that in the length of tyme it had euer mette with: an example, I say, most agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, and the Angells: to see Princesses and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chesses, and other ladyes of the prime nobilitie of Paris, to the number of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98424:46"/> and aboue, deueste them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues of the riche robes ador'<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned with gold and diamants sutable to their Illustrious conditions, and to present themselues in the Hospitalls in the modest attire of simple gentlewomen, with aprons before them, to serue and comfort the most despicable creatures aliue, as comon beggers, portours, and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded soldiers, most nastie and gastly to behold. And this they make their businesse, and goe seriously about it, as a thinge (you would say) belonging to them, of dutie, without discouering the least nicenesse or disdaing fulnesse at all. Of this I haue often bene an eye witnesse any tyme
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98424:47"/> these 32. yeares and vpwards, and all Paris will testifie it till this day.</p>
               <p>Nor doe they goe for fas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hions sake, and by way of diuertisment, but as their hartes are full of compassion vpon the beholding of such sade obiects, so are their mouthes full of consolation and instruction, and their hands noe lesse replenished with charitable presēts, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the infirmities of tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, otherwise, contemptible creatures (if they did not eye poore Christe in them) as confeitures, bisquit, gelee cheries, rosted paires and aples with sugar, and the like; which the pouertie of the Hospitalls could not ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:98424:47"/> afford to so vaste num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Wheras those good Ladys made plentifull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision therof, in euery kinde, in a chamber neere adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge, which they hyred to that purpose: and euerie day by turnes, foure of them, performed that pious ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of going from bedd to bedd to make the distributiō, with an humble meeknesse, well suted to so Christian a worke.</p>
               <p>By these familiar and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing corporall assistances, the good ladyes gayned the harts of those poore people, and in consequence, their soules: for it was obserued that in the space of one yeare, they indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced 700. and sixtie of those
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:98424:48"/> infirme and maymed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons (being some of them Lutherans, some Caluinists, and others Turkes taken at sea) to abiure their heresie, and imbrace the Catholi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e faith, to say nothing of mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multitudes of others who were moued by their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous example, and wholsome aduise, to make generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessions, and to resolue of a more Christian life then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they had ledd.</p>
               <p>Nor did this superlatiue example of Christianitie, keepe within the compasse of what these noble ladyes performed in their owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, but as the nature of Good is to be communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, it spred it selfe not onely
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:98424:48"/> all ouer Paris, but euen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to many remote vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, and Dioceses, to the extreame solace, and reliefe of poore honest families, who were as litle accustomed to begge their bread, as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise litle able to gayne it by their daylie labours.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The institution of the Charitie in the most of, or euen all, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishes rf Paris.</head>
                  <p>THE blessed example of these great Ladyes ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as the primum mobile vnder God to incite other Ladyes of an inferiour ranke togeither with many honest and vertuous bourgesses of the best sorte, to emulate thē
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98424:49"/> in so blessed a practise, and it had indeede so powerfull an influence vpon them, that the most, or euen all the Parishes of Paris, haue meetings, at least euerie monthe (being all associated togeither in a holy conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aternitie) to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer and conferre vpon the necessities of their respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue Parishes, at the Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes house, and accordingly by collections among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to prouide reliefe for them. The distribution of their charitable collections was first performed by the good ladys owne hands, who tooke the paines to goe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site the poore and sicke of the Parishe, and take a more particular assurance of each
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:98424:49"/> ones necessitie; but in a smale tyme they were taught by experience, that some other course was to be taken to carie on so pious a worke effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually: for they found that partly the care of their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie could scarce dispence with their absence, partly their husbands had noe great sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in their conuersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with such infirme and nastie poore people; but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially because they sawe that their smale strength and skill, in that kind, came not home to the necessities of the sicke. Wherfor they aduised of some better way. And Mr Vincent their <hi>adiutor in oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitatibus</hi> was consulted; and he who neuer was at a losse
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98424:50"/> to inuent meanes to promote charitie, found out, and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a constant and effectuall way to continue the worke, and it was this.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="article">
               <head>The institution of the sisters of the Charitie. <hi>ARTICLE XIV.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>M<seg rend="sup">RS</seg>. le Gras, somety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me wife to Mons. le Gras Secretarie to Queene Margarite, now widdowe; Whose mayden name was Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilac of the familie of the most vertuous and famous Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celour of that name. Who as she was of an extraction which promised much, so she was bredd in a schoole which taught more: to witt, in that
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98424:50"/> of the most famous, eloquent and pious Camus Bishope of Bellay, who was knowne to haue bene a great louer, and practiser of pouertie, and might easily theach her what himselfe practised, he being her spirituall directour, till he deliuered her vp into Mr Vincents hands, where she was like to loose nothinge in point of her propension to serue the poore. This ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous lady, was the person pitched vpon by her present Directour as the prime instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the designed set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement. And certainly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine prouidence was as much in this choyce, as her vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings were blessed with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable successe. For she
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:98424:51"/> beinge wholy addicted to the seruice of the sicke, he tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her vp in that way, to fitt her for some greater worke for the future and made her make he first essayes in the villages of diuerse Dioceses, where there were otherwise noe hospitalls to succour the poore and sicke: as in that of Beauuais, Paris, Sanlys, Sois<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, Meaux, Chaalons, and Charters. In all which with incredible paines, being one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie accompained with some other gentlewomen, and a mayde, she setled confrater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities which last till this day. But while he and she had noe other designe but this lowlie way in the villages, God had a greater designes vpon them
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:98424:51"/> to bring it into the great towne of Paris, where she is made the mother of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of course countrie maydes, which he inuented for certaine aydes to the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Dames of Paris, to the effect intimated as aboue.</p>
               <p>They are called maydes or sisters of the charitie, and were instituted by Mr Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent to serue the poore, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially those that are sicke, as he had alreadie instituted Missions of men to preach to the poore. Mrs le Gras was the woman who was putt to instruct them in vertue, and to breade them vp, and to fashion them to the end for which they are gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geither, to witt, to assiste the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:98424:52"/> Dames of Paris to serue the sicke in their Parishes, in the Hospitalls, or where els they may be called. As they are brought vp by that good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in humilitie, patience, and painfull labours, agreable to their end, so are they suted to it in their attire, which is a plaine course gray coate, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out welt or gard, made close to their body, with a close plaine cheife to their heade and their imployment is to carie the potage pot betwixt two of them, vpon a staffe all vp and downe the parishe (which they keepe as bright as the hollander doth his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derns) and to distribute broth and meate, with other neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:98424:52"/> to the needie, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the exigencie of their seuerall wants. This pott is prepared by turns in the burgishesse house of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraternitie, who are lyable to afford fire and seasoning, the rest being supplyed by the mutuall collections of the Parishe. Mr Vincents pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and pietie regulated all these proccedings by cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions which he gaue to the congregation or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the said mayds, of the charitie, seruants of the poore which by his credit, he gott to be approued by the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishope of Paris, in the yeare 1642. and to be authorised and confirmed by the kinges letters patents verified in the Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="article">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:98424:53"/>
               <head>Of an Hospitall of old men and women founded in S. Lazars suburbs by Mr Vincent. <hi>ARTICLE XV,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LET him that is iust be still more iustified, and him that is holy be more and more sanctified, saith the word of truth. In charities commerce there is noe stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a stand; if she cease to acte, she ceaseth to bee, She perfectly well resembles fire which neuer leaues off bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as longe as it can meete with matter to worke vpon. Thus it fared with this holy hart wherin charitie raigned:
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:98424:53"/> he let noe occasion passe wherin he might render glorie to God, and seruice to his poore neighbour. And as where charitie is knowen per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to raigne, she easily drawes the hartes of all men to her seruice, so in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, he was not obliged to goe abroade to seeke the occasion, but it was freely presented to him, without his care, or euen the least thought of it. To witt, a good Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesse of Paris came of his owne accorde, to Mr Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents chamber, who, as it appeares, had learnt the true way of trading for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen (for he was not willing that his left hand should knowe what his right
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98424:54"/> hand did, least vanitie should robbe him of some purt of his purchace) his money he was most willing to giue him, or euen to steale it vpon him; but he was not willing to lend his name to owne the gifte, but it was freely giuen, and vpon noe other condition, or obligation then this, that his name should neuer (be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, would vanitie haue indented) be knowen, as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie would haue it: and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deede it neuer was knowne to this daye for he had mette with a stewards who was noe lesse religiously carefull in that behalfe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en himselfe: so that one may truly say <hi>ama nes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciri &amp; pro nihilo reputari,</hi> might haue bene both their mottos
<pb n="[1]07" facs="tcp:98424:54"/> and that so truly, that could the executour of that chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table worke, haue bene as easily concealed, as the giuer therof; neither of their names, I dare well say, had euer bene knowen. Be the giuers of such pure gifts blessed for euer, whose actions are so much more prayse-worthy, by how much the Donours ayme at lesse prayse.</p>
               <p>There was, it seemes, noe lesse care vsed by the trustee to conceale the summe giuen, then the name of the pious giuer, since it is shutt vp in these indefinite tearmes: <hi>A considerable summe</hi> yet the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment which the good steward made of it, will he nill he, discouers it to haue
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:98424:55"/> bene so considerable, that it must needes haue passed one hundred thousand liures french, or ten thousand pis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolls: for with it, he purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced two houses, a competent garden, and furnished it with all necessaries, togeither with an answearable liuelyhoode for fortie persons; to witt, twentie men and as many wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which where still to be poore old decayed tradsmen &amp;c. All these he disposed of in two different houses, the women being separated from the men, which yet he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triued so ingeniously, that one Masse said in a litle chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and one reader at table serued for them both. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted one of his Missioners
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:98424:55"/> to say their masse, to instructe them, and to administer the sacraments: and some of the sisters of the charitie, to assiste and serue them. This house he called the <hi>Hospitall of the name of Iesus;</hi> and passed a declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this fundation before Notaries, without the name of the Founder at all, that a new name may be giuen him in heauen. And it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by my lord Archbis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hope of Paris, and ratified by the kinges letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="article">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:98424:56"/>
               <head>Of the charities which he procured for the poore cryminells con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to the Gallies. <hi>ARTICL XVI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHILE he was setlinge a liuelyhoode for these poore artificers, who through their age were not able to gayne their liueing, his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion was called vpon, to assiste others who are scarce worthy to li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. These were the Gallislaues, whose double miserie he eyd not withstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge with much pittie. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of conscience he knew they could haue none, being burdened with crymes: nor
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:98424:56"/> comfort of body, being loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with chaynes, and excesse of want and miserie. And yet he knew too, that to eomfort the comfortlesse, be the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect what it will, neuer ceased to be a worke of mercy. He doubted not but that their crymes well deserued what they suffered, and that a iust verdict had condemned them to noe more then a condigne punishment, in sending them to the Gallies. Yet he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued withall that it was not the iudges sense, that they should perish at Paris, who were sentenced to suffer at Marseilles: and iudgement without mercy to those that shew not mercy.</p>
               <p>He takes, then, their sadd
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:98424:57"/> and comfortlesse condition seriously into his harte. He instantly applyes his most humble submissions and sutes to kinge Lowis the 13. and the Magistrates, in their be halse; and obtaynes the old towre at S. Bernards gate for their habitation, till they amount to a competent number to be sent away, accordinge to custome. Thus by his care are they prouided of lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. But where must foode be found for body and soule? There is he called to a further sollicitude, and charitie, which neuer fayles, finds it out▪ Foode for their bodys, for a while, issues out of his owne, and Mrs le Gras smale stocke. And for their soules,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:98424:57"/> the pious priests of S. Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las de Chardonnet, and his owne Missioners, plentifully furnishes. But soone after, the diuine prouidēce abundantly prouides: for a person of Paris of a vaste fortune, left by last will and testament, 6000. l. a yeare for euer for the releife of those miserable creatures, whose deserts could lay clayne to nothinge. This plentifull founde is left vnder the administration of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatour Generall of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for perpetuitie. And wheras the said place of their aboade, was in the Parishe of S. Nicholas de Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donnet, the Curate therof was lyable to administer the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments to them, and to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:98424:58"/> burie then deade corps, which being a great burden for that poore litle Parishe, Mr Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent preuayled with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministratours to allow the said preists 300 l. per annum out of the Funde; vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that they should be obliged to say their Masse, to exhorte and catechise them; and performe other spirituall functions requisite, which they discharge most worthily, and with verie great care and charitie.</p>
               <p>Thus were the poore Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerians well prouided for du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their stay at Paris. But what may become of them after their departure from their good foster-father, God knowes. <hi>Yet as his prouidence</hi>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:98424:58"/>
                  <hi>reacheth from end to end mightily, and disposeth all thinges sweetly,</hi> he inspires his heauenlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes touching his creatures, into the hartes of seconde causes, to be executed by them. Tho they seeme then to be separated from Mr Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, his sollicitudes followe them, the golden chaynes of charitie lincke him to their chaynes of iron to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie them: nay his care runs before them to Marseilles to prepare them a better lodging then they could expect, or their vnhappie predecessours euer inioyed. To this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede he was partly moued by a motiue more humane then ordinarie, though otherwise a most Christian one. He had
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:98424:59"/> formerly bene taken vpon the Mediterranian sea, and caried slaue into Barbarie, where he found but rude intertayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, so that he could say with the Poete <hi>non ignora mali miseris succurrere disco.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>The taste I'ue had of their distresse.</l>
                  <l>Hath wonne my harte to their redresse</l>
               </lg>
               <p>He forthwith applyes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to the most Eminent Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of Richelieu, who was then generall of the Gallies, and to Madame la Duchesse of Aiguillon, his vertuous neece: represents to them the miserable state of the Gallie-slaues; and the extreame want of a Hospitall for them, where they might be assisted in the tyme of their sicknesse. Their pietie procured that such an
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:98424:59"/> Hospitall was built. Here againe was a house, but other helpes were, as yet, wanting. Wher vpon Mr Vincent had resourse to the bountie of that most constantly religious Queene Regent, mother (to kinge Louis the 14. who now happly raignes) whose me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie is in eternall benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to deale with him to become the Founder of this Hospitall; which was done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, by his letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes in the yeare 1645. and was indowed by his Maiestie with 12000. liures or 12. hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pistolls. The blessed effects of this royall charitie you may partly know by a letter written to Mr Vincent, by a most charitable gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:98424:60"/> of Prouence, called Mr de la Coste, who had much contributed to that worke. His letter was as followes.</p>
               <p>These are to giue you an accompt of the progresse of the Hospitall which was espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially established by your pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curement. You will haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstoode by my last, how after much resistance, by the helpe of our lord and Master, they gaue vs vp those that were sicke in the Gallies. Certes I am not able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse the ioy which those poore slaues receiued, when they sawe themselues trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported from that hell, to the said Hospitall, which they tearme a Paradise, where, at their verie entrie, they seeme
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:98424:60"/> cured of halfe their sicknesse, when they are freed from their vermine wherof they were full. Their feete are first washed, and then they are layd in a bedd, a litle softer then the borde wheron they were wonte to lye. And they are quite ouerioyed to finde themselues lodged, serued, and treated, with a litle more charitie then they were in the Gallie, whither we haue sent backe a number of conuales<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes who had bene deade if they had remayned there. Truly Sr we may well say that God hath blessed this worke which appeares not onely in the conuersion of badd Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, but euen of the verie Turkes who crye for holy Baptisme.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:98424:61"/>
               <p>The things which I haue hitherto related are part of the new, fresh, growing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of charitie daylie practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in Paris; and so placed in the cleare light, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to euery ones view, that the highth of malice hath noe specious ground to lye vpon. And vpon such workes I am resolued especially to insiste, least I might meete with the old songe, the Catholikes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede haue formely bene ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie holy, but as truth is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished among them, so hath charitie and sanctitie forsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them. <hi>As to truth perishing</hi> the cōtrarie hath bene againe and againe made good by better penns then myne, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer myne hath not bene wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:98424:61"/> neither according to my smaler talent. But touching pietie, &amp;c. we wishe noe other tryall then the euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Maxime: <hi>by their frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes you shall knowe them.</hi> And vpon this satisfactorie way shall the rest of my labour be imployed.</p>
               <p>I haue sometymes, vpon the contemplation of the great diuersitie of the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of Paris, passed some solitarie moments, to trye whether I could inuent some new well imployed charitie which the ingenious pietie of some good people had not alreadie found out, and prouided for: and truly I hardly find it feasible: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in point of corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:98424:62"/> or spirituall workes of mercy. Such prouisions are made both for body and soule, of persons of all ages, sexes, and conditions, and infirmities of all kindes; as in the series of this discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se will appeare. Shall we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with those which newly begin to fall into the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this world? They are prouided for, before they haue yet the sense to know it. Or els with those that haue so longe experienced the said miseries, that they are become fitter for the graue then the world? The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is prouision also made for them, to liue comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and to end their dayes happily. To be short, the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:98424:62"/> blinde, the lame, the poore, the sicke of what curable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sease soeuer, find charitable retreates for their solace and reliefe. Nay the studious and inuentiue charitie of some generous soules, stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to outuie (as it were) all the rest, haue founded a spacious and noble habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for such as are past all hope of cure; where, in that deplorable and desperate condition, they are assisted and solaced with all the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie and sweetnesse ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="article">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:98424:63"/>
               <head>Of the Hospitall of the holy Ghost situated neere the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne house, in a place called the Greue. <hi>ARTICLE XVII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO begin then to decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the particular cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Paris, how can we take a better rise then from the God of Charitie, or euen God-Charitie the holy Ghost (whence this Hospitall ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes its name) from whose holy inspirations, both this, and all other workes of Charitie doe originally flowe. It is he who inspires the first good thought of it, he
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:98424:63"/> who workes the will, and performance. <hi>Ipse facit vt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciamus.</hi> Saith S. Augustin.</p>
               <p>They that were thus inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red were a companie of Bourgesses of good note, who were moued to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion by a miserable spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle of poore children, who through their parents death, or extreame want, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re reduced to such pouertie that they were readie to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish with hunger and cold. They repaired to the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hope of the place, who ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a many of them into a Confraternitie to haue a ioynt care to releeue those poore children, which pious office till this day they cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably complie with, as their
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:98424:64"/> predecessours had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; and that so throughly too, that they ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue them not onely their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and paines, while they were stronge, and well able; but euen themselues too growne old, with all their substance; and so happily ended their dayes among them: and therby it prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and grew vpp to what it now is.</p>
               <p>The establishment as it was begun for the necessitie of the poore children of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rihs, so it is limited to them alone. In such sorte that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne can be admitted there, but children borne in Paris or the suburbs, in lawfull mariage, whose fathers and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:98424:64"/> mothers are deade; bastards and others found in the stree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes being excluded, as well by the Rules of the house, as by the Kings letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes. How beit these others are well prouided for, as you haue seene aboue, by Mr Vincents care, and his good Ladys cost, which would properly haue belonged to this place, but that I was vnwilling to diuide what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to that holy man.</p>
               <p>These poore children qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified as aboue, are euen ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the breast into this Hospitall, where they are prouided of nourses at the cost therof, and are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully visited and treated. As
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:98424:65"/> they grow vp, they are putt to some trade, as well to masters who reside in the said Hospitall, as to others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade.</p>
               <p>Such of the boyes, as they find of good witts, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise capable, are bredd vp in learning, and become cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giemen: or els, as well they, as the girles, are prouided for in religion, at the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Hospitall, if they haue a will and inclination to that holy course of life.</p>
               <p>The rest are disposed of to serue some persons of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. The boyes which haue learnt any trade, are helped to passe Master. And the girles are assisted with some
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:98424:65"/> certaine summe of money to marie them. And being come to lawfull age, what euer they may haue brought with them, is restored to all of them in generall without limitation.</p>
               <p>They are clothed in decent apparell, of a violet coulour. There are at this day some 200. in the house. And besides those, as many as make vp, in all about 230. or 240. at nourse? To all these the common Charities of Paris giue subsistance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="article">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:98424:66"/>
               <head>Of the Hospitall of the Blessed Trinitie in S. Denys streete. <hi>ARTICLE XVIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OCCASIONS, and emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent necessities furnish men with inuentions, we being still called vpon by nature, to prouide for that which we feele most presse vpon vs. By the instinct of the holy spirit, there was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie prouision made for the poore fatherlesse chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Paris. But there we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re an aboundance of others, in and about the towne, who had both father and mother,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:98424:66"/> and remayned yet in a more lamentable condition, then those that are depriued of them both. These might pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish indeede through want of succour, yet being in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r baptismall innocencie, they would be eternally happie. Wheras those others, by their necessitous and wicked parents, are trayned vp in idlenesse, ignorance, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, their parents owne tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de (made their miserable childs-parte) and by that badd Arte, to which they needed noe master, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come able cheates, cut pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and theeues, and so by that accursed trading often gayne a halter and hell to boote. The Prouost of the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:98424:67"/> Marchands and Magistrates were excited by this proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble occasion of future mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife to the citie, to studie the preuention of it, and to turne threatening mischeife, to ptesent mercy. Which was done as followes.</p>
               <p>Two noble Almans, as it seemes to be intimated, had longe agoe purchaced two Acres of Land neere S. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nys gate, out of a pious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe to lodge poore pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, who coming wearie, might sooner meete with a lodging, then, in a manner, with the towne it selfe. To this purpose they raysed from the grownd a noble faire Hall (togeither with some other buildings) of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:98424:67"/> twentie one fadome and a halfe longe, sixe in breadth, and foure in highth within. This in tract of tyme being put to idle, impertinent, and euen profane vses, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Magistrates, out of their wisdome and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, rescued it out of profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and applied it to the worke of mercy, for which it now serues. To witt, they tooke all the boyes which passed seauen yeares of age, out of their poore and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly parents hands, and placed them in this Hospi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, the care wherof was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to fiue honest and able Bourgesses, who proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them of men and may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to serue them.</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:98424:68"/>
               <p>As all beginings are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, so was this in particular: Their smale begining stocke, would hardly reach to two meales a day, till the chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of some Bourgesses ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their smale pittance.</p>
               <p>They are clad in blew coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and capps: and the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce affords them foode, and instruction, till they growe vp to the yeares of discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then they are bound apprentises to certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne iourneymen of diuers tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, who to this pourpose are admitted to liue in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine houses all within the compasse of the Hospitall for certaine yeares, and by that meanes to passe Masters. a priuiledge which the towne
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:98424:68"/> allowed of, for the good of those poore children, who by this meanes are inabled to gayne their liuelyhoode ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly by their Labours, without being a burden, or a mischeife to be towne, &amp;c. They amount at present to the number of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fiftie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="article">
               <head>Of the Hospitall of les enfans rouges, or Gods children, as a Kinge of France would haue them called: in the streete Portfoin neere the Temple. <hi>ARTICLE XIX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PROVISION being alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die made, as you haue
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:98424:69"/> heard, for poore orfants of Paris as well boyes as girles; as also for boyes taken out of the hands of wicked pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, inuentiue Charitie setts vpon another Hospitall for the assistance of other fatherlesse, and motherlesse boyes, of the villages round about Paris, being about ten or twelue yeares of age, or vnder. This blessed worke was founded by that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady Margarite Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of Nauarre, and Duches<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se of Bar, whom Bel forest qualifies, The Mirour of the Ladyes of her tyme. To this the charitie of good people contributed, and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tract of tyme built a new Chapell and other lodgings.
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:98424:69"/> These are clothed in rede, to intimate charitie, and as well these, as the blew boyes, gayne parte of their liuely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode, by carying torches at the fureralls of such as desire them. They are now onely about a matter of fortie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="article">
               <head>Of the Hofpitall called the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sericorde or worke of Mercye. <hi>ARTICLE XX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CHARITIE still finds new worke, and touches christian hartes to complie therwith. As it did that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble harte of the seconde Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident in Parliament Mr An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonie Seguier by name,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:98424:70"/> worthy vncle to his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse the now Chancelour of France, (of the same na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me) who followes his pious footestepps, as shall partly be declared hereafter. This Illustrious Patron left no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge vndone which might contribute to the well, and permanent beeing of this great worke, extending it selfe to the number of one hundred girles, who are plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully prouided of all things necessarie. So that certainly this charitie could not mount to lesse, all thinges conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then to thirtie or fortie thousand pounds sterl a vast beneuolence to come all from one bountifull hart and purse.</p>
               <p>For in the first place, he
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:98424:70"/> raysed them a faire and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar house from the grownd, with a verie decent and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent chapell therto adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. The house consists of three quarters (a bodie, as it were, and two armes) the fourth quarter being indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>striously left vnbuilt, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the mornings sun, and so to afford a wholsome ayre to those young children. It contaynes in the first storie (the lower roomes being imployd for refectorie, worke-house, kitchen, washouse and other offices) foure great chambers, singularly well peirsed and ayred: in euery one wherof there are 25. iron bedds with white couerlets, each one hauing her bedd a
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:98424:71"/> part. They are, modestly, hansomely, and wholsomely attired in violet clothe, and decent linen, and well fedd.</p>
               <p>Secondly he hath ordered that they shall all of them be such as want both father and mother: natiues of Paris towne or suburbs: begotten in lawfull mariage, and desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of all assistance.</p>
               <p>Thirdly they must be sixe or seauen yeares old before they can be admitted, where they are enterteyned till they be twentie fiue (vnlesse haply they haue leaue for their owne aduantage to goe to some religious house which desires them, or to some good lady, gentlewoman, or Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesse to serue them, or to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:98424:71"/> learne some trade by their meanes, and assistance) and furnished with all necessaries. They haue ouer each cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a Mistresse to keepe good order among them, and to bread them vpp in vertue, and all conueniente workes, vnder the conduct of a graue Gouernante, and learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of Sorbone, the cheife Gouernour therof 2 fourthly at their departure, the house allowes each one an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred frankes to helpe to setle them in the world, in mariage, or otherwise.</p>
               <p>Finally the wise Founder of it, bequeathed it to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and care of diuers Counsellours and Masters of Request, whereof a person of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:98424:72"/> honour Mr Montholon was the cheife in his kinde; as a graue and learned Doctour of Sorbon is alwayes to be the cheife and immediate Gouernour, especially in spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualitie. The first President of the Parliament, and the Procuratour Generall, are also Surintendants (<hi>honorary</hi>) of this place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="article">
               <head>Of the charities done to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Monasterie called our B. Ladys of Sion by Monsiegneur Peter Seguier Chancelour of France, Luke and Pair &amp;c. <hi>ARTICLE XXI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT had pleased God in his prouidence to make vse
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:98424:72"/> of the singular credit which the graue Doctour Richard Smith, Bishope of Calcedoine had with the great Cardinall Richelieu, to procure the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish nation an entrie into France, in point of founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Monasteries of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious women, in the yeare 1634. which till that tyme was shutt to them. The first that inioyed this grace, were the Chanonesse Regulars of S. Augustines Order, who now liue in the Monasterie of our Ladys of Sion neere S. Victors gate, vnder the gouuerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Madame Marie Tred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of noble extraction, who was their first Abbesse and euen still gouuerns suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfully till this day. The
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:98424:73"/> foresaid most Eminent Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall preuailed with the Christian kinge Lowis the 13. for his letters parents in her name; as also with Mons. de Gondy the most illustrious Archbishope for his permis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and spirituall establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: all which were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward verified in Parliament. Vnder this ample establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they went prosperously on in their holy callinge, and by much care and frugalitie, they liued competently and contentedly of the smale pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions and portions, which euery one brought; without being burdēsome to any, here or els where (for setled foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, or euen any thing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, they neuer had any)
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:98424:73"/> They wrought indeede at that tyme, according to their Rule and constitutions, as well to auoyde idlenesse, as to make ornaments for their young chapell, neuer for any money at all, till by the calamitie of the warrs both here and in England, they were reduced to a necessitie to practise a lesson which they had neuer learnt among their noble pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, (who were wont to liue in plentie, farre aboue the reach of want, as is well kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne). That is, to imploye their hands to contribute to their liuely hoode, which they did, and doe till this day, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h much sweete resignation and vertue, and noe lesse edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to all prudent persons
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:98424:74"/> and benedictions from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon their willing ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours: for indeede some yeares did passe, wherin they scarce receiued sufficient to maintayne their agent, tho the most of their meanes was left at perpetuitie in their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and rich frends hāds, to rayse a standing subsistance. But where the rage of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent rebells left them but litle, much could not be had, nor indeed euen any thinge for some yeares space, when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion was at the highth. In the meane tyme a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of fiftie and more poore gentlewomen, being cutt oft from their owne, are left to Gods prouidence among stangers.</p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:98424:74"/>
               <p>Nor can we iustly doubt, but that sweete prouidence which extends it selfe to the feeding of the inconsiderable birds of the ayre, failes not in extreamities to assiste those who in the first place make it their businesse to seeke the kingdome of God, and his iustice: and fayle not withall to contribute what they are able to their necessarie subsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, by the moderate la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of their handes in cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitous tymes. Worthily ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for may they thinke, that in that coniunture, Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence guided that famous Chancelour to their poore house, of which haply he had neuer heard, till a good neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour the <hi>Apelles,</hi> or rather the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:98424:75"/>
                  <hi>Raphel,</hi> of our Age Mons. le Brune, who had the honour of his presence at diner with him, out of his owne good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, without any applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or knowledge of theirs moued his greatnesse to heare their musicke at euensonge; which he did, and pleased to seeme well satisfied therwith. After which he had the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular goodnesse, of his owne accorde, to call for the supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, and rather graciously to offerre his charitable assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, then to stay till he were sued to for it. For Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame, sayes he, I beleeue in this tyme who sayes <hi>English</hi> sayes <hi>poore,</hi> the Abbesse re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyd, my Lord, it is but too true. Why then, quoth he,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:98424:75"/> did you make noe application to me? Alas, said she my Lord, our smale acquaintaine affords vs noe such happinesse as to haue accesse to your Greatnesse: yet in verie deede our reall wants callinge sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly vpon vs, we moued our good friend my Lord mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague in it. He is my good friend too, replyed he, but truly he neuer mentioned it, and said merily, reproche him with it. How beit my said good Lord by his diligence (whose knowen zeale needs noe spurring in pointe of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie) preuented our reproche for the next newes we heard, brought vs one thousād liures from my Lord Chancelours bountie, by his hands, and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:98424:76"/> with in the same yeare, as much more as made it neere vpon 4000. liures or 400. pistolls, togeither with the continuation of his frequent charities, honours, and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full visites of all his numerous and illustrious familie, his powerfull fauour and protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon all emergent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions; so that to Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and his (be it alwayes kept in a gratefull memorie by vs his most oblidged beads women) be it knowen, that that singularly amiable visite of his, has bene worth to there poore house, aboue a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pistolls, which still till this day growes to more and more. Sweete Iesus grante that he and his, may liue pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perously,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:98424:76"/> and in the toppe of honour, and crowne his charities with eternall glorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="article">
               <head>Of the Hospitall in S. Germains suburbs called la petite Maison. <hi>ARTICLE XXII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE children of both sexes being well proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, as aboue, the charitie of the good Magistrates was called to the care of poore aged and distressed persons as well men as women, whose age and impotencie hindered them to gaine their liuing. They are diuided into two quarters, the men liuing a part from the women. This
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:98424:77"/> house was for the most part as well built as indowed by the bountifull charitie of Mr Boulencour counsellour to the kinge, and President of his Chamber des Compts, who erected many lodgings, and chambers for the lame and impotent &amp;c.</p>
               <p>They are furnished with meate, drinke, and all thinges necessarie from the <hi>Grand Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaux des pauures,</hi> as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called, which is, in effect the great Court of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in order to workes of charitie: of which I intend to make a particular description here after.</p>
               <p>Further this Hospitall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues poore vagabonds, as well boyes as girles, who haue
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:98424:77"/> gotten scauld pates, by lying in the streetes, or vnder shopp stalls or otherwise, who are diligently dressed, purged, and frequently cured, as it hath happened to aboue 200. in this place.</p>
               <p>Here are also receiued poore women who are subiect to the falling sicknesse, as also others who are distracted, and run vp and downe the streetes in a frantike manner: who yet by good vsage, are often in length of tyme, recouered to their witts.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Grand Bureau de pauures,</hi> prouides this house of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour who is at present a verie able surgeon, who out of his singular charitie makes
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:98424:78"/> choyce to dwelle amōgst those miserable creatures, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be able to assiste them. And he is so farre from in. riching him selfe by his loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some practise, that contrarily he freely spends his owne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes vpon them, in making many medicaments and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, with hopes to cure their desparate infirmities (as it often happens) or at least to solace their paines. This good man has another of the same profession to assiste him in that blessed imployement. He liues neere to the place, and fayles not to be with them euery day, or euen as oft as he is called for, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie the remedies which the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:98424:78"/> other prouides, according to his order.</p>
               <p>And wheras this place serues also for a house of correction, there are two prisons to tame incorrigible persons; and to that effect there are foure Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters taken out of charitie (by reason of some infirmitie) as the rest are, who are orderd to watch ouer the comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the poore, in point of words, or actions, or any inueterate vice they may haue contracted in their rude edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and accordingly to reprehend them by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours direction. This is not one of the least charities of Paris, by reason of the strange subiects they are to
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:98424:79"/> deale withall, wher of some through their decrepit age neede continuall assistance: others in respect of their irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and accidentall deseases must alwages haue eyes vpon them: others want witt either to assiste themselues, or to render themselues capable of assistance without much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: and others finally through their rudenesse and incorrigiblenesse, deserue noe assistance at all, vnlesse cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie taught christians to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der good for euill. And to serue Iesus-Christ in the worst of his members.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="article">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:98424:79"/>
               <head>Of the Hospitall of the 300. blind men comonly called the Quinze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingt, or the 15. tymes twentie. <hi>ARTICLE XXIII</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HITHERTO we haue seene young and old; men and women; fatherlesse and motherlesse boyes and girles; well prouided for, by the pietie of Paris: it must also extend it selfe to their comfort who are euen depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the comfort of the light. This was longe agoe the care of a greate kinge and S. Lowis, who was the first Foundour of this spacious familie. The first occasion of
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:98424:80"/> it, as is deliuered by Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forest in the first Tome of his Annalls, was the misfortune of three hundred gentlemen who hauing bene left Hostages in the Holy Land, by the said kinge, were trecherously and cruelly sent home to him with their eys putt out, for whom he made this place.</p>
               <p>He built them a large church in a place as then a woode, which is in riched with many holy relickes. Wherof the most pretious, are: a peece of our sauiours crosse Bones of saint Stephen and S. Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert. A peece of the same S. Stephen first Martyr, as also of S. Matthew the Apostle and S. Blaise. Bones of S. Laurence. Bones of S. Iohn,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:98424:80"/> S. Paule, S. Martin and S. Hilarie, with many more.</p>
               <p>This church is inriched also with may graces and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons from Rome, granted by Pope Alexander at this holy kinges instance, which for the better vnderstanding of Indulgences, so well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by this B. Pope, aboue 400. yeares agoe, I haue thought good to giue in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish word for word as we haue it in the said Bull.</p>
               <p>Alexander Bishoppe, ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of the seruants of God, health and Apostolicall Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction to his most deare and Illustrious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onne in Christ Lowis kinge of France. Tho he from whose gift it comes, that his faithfull doe serue
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:98424:81"/> him worthlilye, and laudably, doth, out of the abundance of his pietie (which outstrips as well the deserts and desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the suppliantes) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre more vpon such as serue him, then they can any way merite. Yet desiring to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an acceptable people to God, we inuite them to please him, as it were, by certaine alluringe presents, to witt by Indulgences, and remissions cte. that they may be therby more fitted to Gods grace. Wheras therfore (as it was exposed to vs from you) you haue made a house for the blinde of Paris, and built them a church, we desireing that it may be honorably fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, haue releesed one
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:98424:81"/> yeares pardon of the penance which was inioyned, out of Gods mercy, relying vpon the authoritie of the B. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles S. Peter and S. Paule, to all those that are truly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent and confessed, and yearely visite your church to the honour of S. Remy (the Patron therof) vpon the day of his translation, and three monthes immediatly follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing. Datum Anagniae 6. Cal. Aug. Pont. 6. anno.</p>
               <lg>
                  <head>Of the blind men Boterays writes in Latine verse to this effect</head>
                  <l>With in these wals</l>
                  <l>Three hundred blind are found.</l>
                  <l>Which holy Lowis</l>
                  <l>His charitie did found.</l>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:98424:82"/>
                  <l>In lyuerie gowne</l>
                  <l>And st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffe in hand. O strange!</l>
                  <l>They lonely through</l>
                  <l>The Citties Didalls range.</l>
                  <l>Before the day peeps out</l>
                  <l>They're vp and gone</l>
                  <l>(For dayes and nightes</l>
                  <l>To those poore soules, are one)</l>
                  <l>To grope out Churches</l>
                  <l>By the guessing ayde</l>
                  <l>Of their discreeter staffe,</l>
                  <l>Their way is made.</l>
                  <l>It proues their eyes,</l>
                  <l>Their whole supporte and strength</l>
                  <l>Through th'Maze of streetes</l>
                  <l>to bring them home at length.</l>
                  <l>They euery Chapell</l>
                  <l>Church, and altar find.</l>
                  <l>Each corner of the towne;</l>
                  <l>Their staffs not blind.</l>
                  <l>Tho eyes they'ue none.</l>
                  <l>Their learned tongue can prone</l>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:98424:82"/>
                  <l>Their crying wants;</l>
                  <l>And store of brasse is throwne</l>
                  <l>Into their brazen dish:</l>
                  <l>Which they, at leasure</l>
                  <l>Repairing home;</l>
                  <l>Adde to their common treasure.</l>
                  <l>So that their staffe,</l>
                  <l>Their hands and feete, doe giue</l>
                  <l>What eyes refus'd;</l>
                  <l>Enough wheron to liue,</l>
                  <l>Being ioyn'd to that</l>
                  <l>Their Royall Foundour gaue</l>
                  <l>Which then sufficd,</l>
                  <l>But now more ayde doth craue.</l>
                  <l>Be Paris blest,</l>
                  <l>Whose pious hartes can finde,</l>
                  <l>Wherwith to feede the sicke,</l>
                  <l>The lame, the blinde.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="article">
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:98424:83"/>
               <head>Of the Hospitall called the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence. <hi>ARTICLE XXIV</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I had the happinesse to be in person at the establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this pious place: where I sawe a greate solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, the chapell being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie richly adorned, and sett out with daintie mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call deuises, the musike ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, and the sermon most eloquent, made by that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous preacher Mr Lingende Bishope of Sarlate. To witt. that most imcomparably ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Queene Regent, Anne d'Austrice, was there present
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:98424:83"/> not onely to grace the solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, but euen bountifully and religiously to found the Hospitall, bestowing a house and spacious garden vpon the inhabitants, situated in S. Marceaux suburbs, and erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it into a seminarie, where there are alwayes about 80. in number.</p>
               <p>In this are setled a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of graue maydes, who liue most regularly and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarlie in a secular state, being verie grauely and modestly attired, after the manner of good widowes in the world.</p>
               <p>Their blessed imployement is, to receiue, gratis, instruct, and direct (in order to their present and future happinesse) certaine poore maydes, who
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:98424:84"/> are destitute of Parents and meanes, and consequently run great hazard, to loose that which can neuer after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be recouered; and to be putt with all, togeitherwith that irreparable losse, into the high way of perdition. But Gods prouidence so or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that they were deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the snare of the Fowlers, and they can happily singe with the Psalmist: <hi>the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are is bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ē, and we are deliuered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meane while all the other pious inuentions of Paris, had not reached to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention of this danger: for howeuer there are multitudes of hospitalls for the educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of poore girles of a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner condition, yet these be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:98424:84"/> for the most parte, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen of noble extraction and condition, Hospitalls would but verie ill sute with hartes borne to better, which according to humane frayltie flesh and bloode can not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily forgett. This therfor was left to the ingenious and noble charitie of a Royall breast, Anne of Austrice, who as she had a heauenly Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, that was the mother of the immaculate Virgine, so was she a fitt Patronesse to protect Virgines in earth.</p>
               <p>It was her care then, and withall liberalitie, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided them of this safe sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarie, where they are secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the arrowe flying in the day, from businesse wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:98424:85"/> in the night, from inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and the midday deuill. And while they happily liue in this holy vacancie from danger, they so improue themselues in vertue, and fine workes, that some of them become capable therby, to be admitted into some charitable monasterie: others in tyme, meete with maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges sutable to their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and some finally by their ripenesse in vertue, and care to follow the foostepps of their Mistresses, are iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged fitt to be made Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresses themselues, and to remayne there, to exhibite the like charitie to others, as they themselues had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="article">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:98424:85"/>
               <head>Of the Hospitall named la Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in S. Germain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> suburbs. <hi>ARTICLE XXV.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THIS is gouerned by a certaine companie of Religious men of the Order of a holy man called blessed <hi>Iean de Dieu,</hi> or Iohn of God, the first Institutour of the same, vnder the Rule of S. Augustine. They adde to the three essentiall vowes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that of seruing the sicke all their life longe. An excellent Institute, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution worthy of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, who giue to the world a conuincing testimonie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that the loue of God is
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:98424:86"/> in their hartes, since purely for the loue of him whom they see not, they loue his litle ones whom they see: and not in bare words, and discourse, but in the deede doing, and in truth, since the performance of the worke, is an infallible proofe of the truth of loue.</p>
               <p>The extent of their Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties goes thus farre, that they admitt of all poore sic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, and wounded persons, of the Male sexe, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, saue onely such as haue incurable, or contagious deseases.</p>
               <p>The Hospitall itselfe is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly built, well situated, and as neatly kept as most pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate houses in the towne.
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:98424:86"/> What is wholy deputed to the vse of the sicke, consists of three longe galleries or Halls. Wherof the greatest conteynes eightie foure verie hansome bedds, with decent curtins, and is especially imployed to receiue honest poore Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesses, whose house it may seeme to be (so ordinarily are they lodged there.) The second is garnished with 32. bedds equall to the former; and it is wholie alloted for wounded men. The third conteynes 22. bedds, and is for younge boyes who are cutt for the stonne.</p>
               <p>As to their manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the sicke, it is full of humilitie and myldnesse. At their arriuall one of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:98424:87"/> washes their feete, which was the ancient and good manner of hospitalitie. Then they are layd in a bedd alone, as all the rest are (saue the litle children) with faire cleane sheetes, cleane shir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, pillibeers, night-cappes, and a table-napkin: as also a night gowne, pantoples, a basin to spitt in, and a pott and a cupp to drinke in.</p>
               <p>Their manner of treating the sicke, is, to haue them visited by the Doctour euery day once at least, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Infirmarian, the the Apothecarie, and the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, who orders what phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke they are to take, what to eate, drinke, &amp;c. And still from three houres to
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:98424:87"/> three houres, they take some thinge or other to refreshe and comfort them; as new-layed egges, brothe, a coulis, gelee, or comfeitures. In fine those, good religious neuer deserte them day nor night, but watche with them by turnes.</p>
               <p>For the good of their sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les they are auertised vpon their first cominge, to prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re themselues to make a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall confession, as the most excellent and necessarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, Gods mercyfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence oft permiting our corporall sicknesses, for the cure of our spirituall infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. Either then present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in case they be dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously sicke, or at least the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:98424:88"/> next day, they receiue the holy communion, which is brought to them by the priest before Masse, being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigned by all the religious which goe all processionally (with waxe-candles in their hands) singing the <hi>Pange lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua,</hi> and <hi>Veni Creator.</hi> After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they heare Masse eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, which is said in the same place, with many other antems and prayers sunge by the Religious. They are also taught their Christian do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, thrice a weeke, and besides that a religious is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to instruct them mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re particularly in point of their prayers, the Sacraments, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Before dinner and supper
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:98424:88"/> they are ordered to say <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Aue,</hi> for their Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factours, while the Religious recite the Psal. <hi>Miserere,</hi> and <hi>De Profundis,</hi> and then they washe their hands, and heare the blessinge of the table said with a lowde voyce.</p>
               <p>When any one is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously sicke, and drawinge towards his Agonie, all the religious are called togeither by rynging the bell, and come with lighted tapers in their hands, to say the prayers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Church in such circumstances. That do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne there is a religious left with them, to assiste and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them till death.</p>
               <p>Being deade, they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently and religiously brought
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:98424:89"/> out and buried; all the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious being present with ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted torches in their hāds, who say the office of the deade, and singe the Masse of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiem for the good of their soules.</p>
               <p>And indeede all thinges are so well disposed in this place, and euen so gentilly, regularly, and religiously, as to all conueniences, which concerne either body or soule, that I haue oft tymes seene, not onely good Burgesses, but withall persons of greate qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, make choyce of it in their sicknesse. And some of thē were so much edified with that religious traictement, that a pious Knight of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland returned home so well
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:98424:89"/> seasoned with the agreeable odour of that excellent cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, which he saw done to any without exception) that by his last will and Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he bequeathed 900. liu. ster to that blessed place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="article">
               <head>Of the Hospitall Generall. <hi>ARTICLE XXVI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HITHERTO hath my pen bene imployed in the description of the lesser hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalls, which I looked vpon as the smaler brookes which fruitfully water the poore mans field: but now I am falling into a Vast Ocean of Charities, where it is hard to discouer either land or limite
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:98424:90"/> It is called, but one (<hi>Hospitall Generall</hi>) but branches it sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe into sixe vaste places. That which beares the name, and has the surintendance of all the rest, is situated in S. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors suburbs (close by the Abbaye of that name) and is knowne by a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular name, <hi>our Ladys of Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> which the Masters and Administratours of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce built, having to that pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, bought diuers houses and gardens, and alloted them all to receiue, lodge, and nourish poore old women, and younge girles, wherof there are at this houre twelue hundred and odde.</p>
               <p>The Hospitalls depending vpon this, are, the Salpetri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:98424:90"/> Biscestre, Scipion, the Teignierie, and the Sauonne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. In which sixe places, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue 8000. poore creatures are conteyned, and maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at present, by the care of the kinge, and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, and the free and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon charities of all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which is receiued in sma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le trunkes or boxes, placed in Churches and shopps, all the towne ouer.</p>
               <p>The Salpetriere is farre the most ample of all these pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, being built from the ground in a faire and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar quadrangle, and is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of foure or fiue thousand persons. It is finely situated in a medowe, by the ryver side, ouer against the Arce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:98424:91"/> It was especially depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the vse of vagabonds and beggers, which importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and infested all Paris, whither they swarmed from all the Prouinces. It is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, in the vse of it, into three quarters. One quarter is imployed to logde poore families not otherwise able to liue. Another for men who are oblidged to worke according to their abilities. And the third for litle gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, euen from two yeares old.</p>
               <p>Scipion is in S. Marceaux suburbs, and is wholie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in a worke of singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar charitie. To witt, poore women with child who haue not meanes at home to be
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:98424:91"/> brought to bedd, are freely receiued there, brought to bedd, and lye inn, being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided of nourses and all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges fitting in such a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The Castle of Biscestre, is an ancient building standing a litle out of S. Victors su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs. It is for those who haue strength and abilitie to worke. There are in it at this tyme, about 1800. men, who are kept closely to the exercise of their diuers tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</p>
               <p>The Teignerie is in S. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains suburbs, and is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to keepe 120. who are troubled with scauld hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. As the sauaterie is allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the charitable inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynement
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:98424:92"/> of 60. poore sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie boyes.</p>
               <p>Now as this is the thinge of most publicke and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall concerne of all the rest, as being a royall establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and royally endowed by his Maiesties liberall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessions in many kinds. And as the end of it, is, not onely to releeue the poore for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent but to preuent pouertie and beggerie for the tyme to come, greate arte and industrie is vsed, to trayne vp the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger sorte in such manufactu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, as may alwayes afford them an honest liuelyhoode: and others, who though stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and lustie, and well able to worke, yet chused rather to liue in idlenesse, and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:98424:92"/> their breade, are now taught, and forced to gayne it by their labours. Which, that it might be followed without any interruption, it is ordered by publicke au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, that when any of them chances to be sicke, they are transported to the Hostel Dieu that generall <hi>Refugium afflictorum</hi> which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer refuseth any.</p>
               <p>Hence it is that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test officers of his Maiesties Courts of Iustice, Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp;c. are intrusted and take a religious concerne in the management of this vaste worke, in qualitie of honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Suruisours, hauing store of able, honest, and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente Burgesses, to putt in
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:98424:93"/> in execution, what by their frequent assemblies, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, is found most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceing to the publike weale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare.</p>
               <p>And noe lesse care is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the spirituall aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement, of those laysie va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabonds, who were too neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectfull of their soules good, and would willingly haue loytered it out, in the stree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and by corners, with too probable hazard of eternall perdition, had they not bene forced in, according to the Gospell, with faire hopes to gayne the day-pennie of Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. This care is princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally left to the wise conduct of a Doctour of Sorbon of great learning and vertuous
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:98424:93"/> reputation. His name is Mr Polier Gouernour of this Hospitall in cheife; Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of the visitation; and of the Carmelits. He hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles himselfe to take a place, and liue among these poore beggers. Which as it is a place of litle splendour, so proues it to him of lesse emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lument, saue onely that it affords him full vtterance for ten or twelue thousand fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes a yeare, which he stood possessed of, in patrimonie or benefices, before he imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that deare beggerlie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrement. <hi>Blessed is the man that walketh not after gold, nor placeth his hopes in the heapes of treasure:</hi> Mr Polier is he, <hi>and we will prayse him.</hi> And
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:98424:94"/> right well may we, since he giues not onely what he has, but euen what he is, himsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, which is harder to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted withall. He giues ouer his tyme to the necessities of the poore, and sacryficeth his repose to their rest. He has the sollicitudes of all the sixe places vpon his owne shoulders, being assisted with a matter of twentie pious Priests, who incessantly, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his directiones, preach, teach, instruct, comfort, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, communicate, &amp;c. who but the Catholike Church alone, is able to shew, such fruites; such men; such man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; such assistances, shewen to the poore for Gods pure loue alone?</p>
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:98424:94"/>
               <p>Here I must not omitte to relate to Gods glorie, and the honour of those excellent <hi>Ladys of the charitie,</hi> so often mentioned aboue with deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued commendations; that they were the first mouers to this vaste worke: for so I finde it, in the first booke and 45. chapter of Mr Vincents life, who was often, in their weekly charitable assemblies, solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, yea importuned by them, to giue way to, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie their zeale in that kinde. But his graue counsell still was, that they went too faste a pace for him (whose custome was to walke slowly) to keepe companie with them, That it was a businesse of so greate importance, and so
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:98424:95"/> vast extent, whether one loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon the manner how to compasse it, or the meanes to mainteyne it, that it required a longe and mature delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For the rest, that he was singularly edified with their zeale, and infinitly blest God in it. And truly he had greate reason to prayse God, who had so inflamed and dilated the hartes of those good La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, that they vsed more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie to be deliuered of their meanes to pious vses, then euen the most couetous wretch to scrape it togeither. The first lady that spoke, had a mynd to be quitt of fiftie thousand liures which she freely offered. The second was readie to oblidge her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:98424:95"/> to giue three thousand liures annuall rent in fine, they assured him againe and againe, that there should be noe want of meanes, since many ladyes of their acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance were resolued to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute in a verie large mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. Good Mr Vincents most tender harte was noe longer able to resiste so deliciously wounding assaults, which he so visibly discouered to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from their loue to God in their poore neighbour, where his saintly soule was inseparably lodged. In a word, he gaue way to their inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble feruour to gett vtterance for their monyes. And to giue testimonie for his owne part that he was noe lesse sure
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:98424:96"/> then slowe, and that at longe runing he was able to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the swifteste charitie. Where vpon he had presently recouse to that heauen-borne breast, the Queene Regente, and obteyned, of her free charitie, the salpetriere, as he had before the castle of Biscestre, which he and those vertuous Ladys, vpon better consideration, and seconde thoughts, freely consigned vpp into the handes of the Magistrates, who had not onelie stronger armes (for stronger and more couragious hartes they could not haue) to wealde so heauie a frame, but by their power withall they were able to call many hands to lighten the burden.</p>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:98424:96"/>
               <p>Meane while those <hi>mulieres fortes,</hi> valiant women, would not be quitte beaten backe. What they were not able wholie to graspe with weake armes, they would not fayle to haue a finger in. Nay they threw notable summes into stronger hands: not much ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe, by whom, so God his worke were done. By their owne, and good fathers, care and coste then, a great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of linnen, beddes, and other moueables, togeither with ten thousand shirtes, by number, were prouided for Gods new house-keepers, to make the poore welcome Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was pouertie so compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently fitted, by so greate Ladys daintie hands; <hi>who</hi>
                  <pb n="192" facs="tcp:98424:97"/>
                  <hi>haue opened them to the needie, and stretched out their palmes to the poore. Let their workes prayse them in the gates,</hi> of heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="article">
               <head>Of the great Hospitall called l'Hostel-Dieu, or Gods house in Englishe, <hi>ARTICLE XXVII</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE perfect description of this vaste familie may well be called <hi>Hic labor, Hoc opus,</hi> a worke rather to be admired, then to be expressed to the full. It is a sea which still so ebbs and flowes, that it is continually high water, still a full sea there. Scarce a day in the yeare passes, but there
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:98424:97"/> are 50. 60. 80. or some tymes 100 new commers, and happly too, a like number may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to make place for their poore neighbours, whether as being recouered, and sent backe to their owne howses, or being sent to their graues. In a word this sea is euer so growing, and so growne, that 20. at least, or 25. thousand, come and returne, or dye in a yeares space. But who are they who receiue all these multitudes of people I pray? who are they, of what towne or countrie? What are they, of what sexe age or condition? What kind of infirmitie brings them thither? Of what reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion must they be? With what letters commendatarie must
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:98424:98"/> they come to be admitted?</p>
               <p>The answers to these Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rees will fully euidence the boundelesse charitie of this blessed house, and shew it to be <hi>Gods House</hi> indeede which is shutt vp from none. Gods I say, who opens his hand and replenisheth euery creature with benediction: who is noe accepter of persons, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his sunne to ryse vpō the good, and the badd: and rayneth vpon the iust and the vniust.</p>
               <p>Whence are they whom they receiue? That question is neuer asked in this place. They see them to be men, and consequently to be their neighbours, according to S. Augustins generall rule, <hi>eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:98424:98"/> man is neighbour to euerie man,</hi> without exception: and if neighbours, those then whom God hath commanded them to loue.</p>
               <p>Of what towne or countrie? that they iudge not necessarie neither, because sith all the waste world is the wise mans countrie, all the inhabitants of the world, are their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie men, vnlesse, haply, that question be asked that they may be better inabled to vnderstand them, and serue them by the helpe of some interpreter, whom their cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie has readie, or endeuours to find out, to which effect I my selfe haue bene sent for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who are they?</hi> That againe as litle troubles the good crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:98424:99"/> They see poore Christ in their infirmitie ād pouertie, &amp; he has iust title to enter into his owne house. Be they men, be they women; be they old be they younge; be they poore be they rich; it imports not; if they be onely sufficiently sicke, they are fitt matter for their spirituall commerce, and in that name alone suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently commended to them: they haue quarters a part for both sexes, and hartes dilated by charitie, euen readie to lodge more then their other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise vast house is capable of. Whence it is that they laye sometymes two, yea or three poore boyes in owne bedd, vpon which I haue obserued some protestant lookeing still
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:98424:99"/> a squinte, eye that particular with more scandall, then all those and other excesses of charitie with edification. <hi>O curuae in terris animae &amp; coelestis inanis! ô animalis homo!</hi> ô ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, or carnall man, who inderstands not what belongs to the spirit? Did they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune any body to come to oppresse them with an ouerplus of labour? Or must charitie be blamed because she has a latitude of harte <hi>to suffer all, to solace all, to doe good to all?</hi> Must they be blamed for chusing rather to saue the liues of two in one bedd, then to suffer one of them to dye on a dunghill, or in a ditch? <hi>Credat iudeus appella haud ego.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What kind of infirmitie
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:98424:100"/> renders them capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admitted there? Marrie euen euery one. Old age, which is it selfe a desease; feauers, goutes, proxes, the stone, woundes receiued in warrs, or by misfortune; any thing, in fine, which either Hypocratis or Galian vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke to cure, saue onely the plague or pistolence. Nor doe they except against them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their owne particular safetie, but for the saftie of all, since while they refuse them there, they goe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, to assiste, and serue them, at the Hospitall of S. Lowis, which is alloted for that purpose alone. In which heroicall seruice, as it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, though diuers of them
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:98424:100"/> haue bene strucken therwith, as some of themselues assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me, yet neuer any of them dyed therof. <hi>Sit nomen Domini benedictum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With what commendatarie letters must they come accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pained? Verily with noe other but their crying miseries, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with the kinge of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens letters patentes written by one of the penmen of the holy G. S. Matth. saying, in the person of Christ, <hi>What you did to these litle ones, you did to me.</hi> How cā euer a more powerfull commendation be addressed to any Christian harte?</p>
               <p>Of what religion must they be? Here indeed, it seemes they might make a refusall not irrationall; since being
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:98424:101"/> sometymes infidelles, they haue but a weake clayme to Christian charities, while they deney Christ: or being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, and not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating with them in the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in vnitie of faith, why should they share with them in the charitable fruites ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? Nay since they obstinatly deney the merites of good workes, in opposition to holy scripture, they merite not at all to participate therin. How euer, none are refused by them, who haue learnt of their holy father, <hi>that to assiste and doe good to euery one, tho they had otherwise hurt vs, or wished our harme, is the true, perfect, and onely religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>According to this vaste,
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:98424:101"/> illimited, Christian way, of charitie they proceede. And as they keepe alwayes a free and open House, so they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer want good store of guests who eate, and drinke, and repose therin, without ere reckoning with their Host, its Gods house, and God payes all. Their ordinarie numbers are alwayes vaste; they haue rarely lesse then 1700. or eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene hundred; often tymes 2000. nay sometymes they passe three thousand, as I was certainly informed by one of the Doctours therof. Yet that great Prouisour <hi>who with fiue barlie loaues and two fishes could sociate a farre greater multitude</hi> in the wilde deserte, can when he pleaseth, and doth in due
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:98424:102"/> tyme, open the hartes and purses of the good Parisians to feede those huge numbers of his distressed members.</p>
               <p>And howeuer their constant annuall reuenues mounte to an immense summe, to witt, to two hundred fiftie eight thousand three hundred and therteene liures french, as it is stated by the Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the place, yet are they still oblidged to haue their hands vp to their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly forterfather for sixtie seauen thousand three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred liuers (some tymes lesse, some tymes more) in comon yeares, which yet out of his singular mercy, neuer fayles to ryse out of the free chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of particular persons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="article">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:98424:102"/>
               <head>Of the first and principall Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders or benefactours of this place, as I find it in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities of Paris. <hi>ARTICLE XXVIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the yeare 660. S. Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry the 28. Bishope of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, in the raigne of kinge Clouis the second, was the first who putt a hand to this holie worke, now called Gods house, where he nourished the poore out of his owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenus. This we find recorded in these tearmes: S. Landry commanded the Hospitall, commonly called the house of God, to be built neere
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98424:103"/> our ladys Church, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the poore out of his owne stocke.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1258. (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gaguin) S. Lowis kinge of France, imployed a great summe, to inlarge the said Hospitall, and to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the reuenus therof, as saith William Nangis in his life.</p>
               <p>The Chapell was built by a Bourgisse of Paris named Gudart Mocreux as appeares vpon a plate of brasse, in old rymes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>A certaine Mocreux by surname,</l>
                  <l>A master changeur of good fame</l>
                  <l>This chapell in Gods house did make</l>
                  <l>May he in's glorie ere partake.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>In the yeare of our Lord 1535. Chancelour Pratte, who
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:98424:103"/> was afterward Cardinall, and Legate in France, made this Hospitall be verie much am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified, by the addition of one spacious Roome which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Legates Hall. He gaue withall a great substance to maintayne the poore of the place, the Religious women, who serue them: and the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, Doctours, and to buy Physicke.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1602. kinge Henry the greate, caused the greate and litle Hall of S. Thomas to be reedified. They were begun the foresaid yeare and were finished in the yeare 1606. togeither with the three massie pillers which were ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed out of the riuer.</p>
               <p>Thus by many hands, and
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:98424:104"/> sundrie additionall ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, at diuers tymes, it grew vp at length into a huge bulke: yet for all that, it was neither answerable to their large hartes, who haue the care of it, nor to the vaste number of the poore and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die which continually super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abounds. What did proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and vaste charitie, which will be confined within noe bounds, suggest in these strai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ttes? Marrie, wheras the land could allowe them noe elbo-roome, the place being limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on all sides (to witt with two streetes, our ladys church, and the riuer) they forced the riuer to afford them place making a bridge ouer the backe of it, vpon which they
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:98424:104"/> haue gayned a faire, large, and longe gallerie, and by that againe, they discouered a way open to a greater inlargemēt: for hauing purchaced a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of old buildings on the other side of the water, they raysed vpon their ruines a stately vaste, and euen a royall quarter, consisting of three most spacious Halls, all of hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en stone. Nor are these and the old halls diuided by the riuer, but it is euen it, which affords a faire large court in the middle of them; which is noe lesse agreeable to the eye then vsefull for the ficke to take the ayre, and to ayre the whole house.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="article">
               <pb n="208" facs="tcp:98424:105"/>
               <head>Of the number of the diuers halls and offices, and the disposition therof. <hi>ARTICLE XXIX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL the anciët building consists of foure great Halls, and seauen offices. The Legats Hall and the new Hall are appointed for sickewomē. The Hall of women brought to bedd, is assigned for their lying inne The Hall of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmerie, is alloted for men that are most sicke. The office of S. Denys, is for those that are wounded. The office of S. Thomas, for sickemen. The office belonging to Dame Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oresse
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:98424:105"/> and three other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, is imployed to winde the deade. The office of the washe-house, is vsed to drie the linen of the sicke, and that of the communitie. The of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Watchers, for those who watch with the sicke fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenne nights togeither. The office of her who keepes the trunke and the Relickes, and dresses the Church, for that vse. The office of the Porter, is deputed to receiue the sicke, to see them visited, lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and confessed: who is withall to giue out bread and wine for them. There is also an Apothecairerie, where oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, salues, and medicinall drogues are kept in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. A great wash house for
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:98424:106"/> all the clothes in generall. A litle one, where thrice a day they wash the linen of such as are more greeuously sicke. The vesterie, out of which the sicke are furnished with bedds, which yet might ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be called the trash house wherin all the poore people's riches, I meane, their ragges, are kept for their vse. There are also many more places, for the Priests (who are ten constātly, besides many others who out of their particular deuotion come frequently to instruct ād comfort the sicke) and domesticall seruants &amp;c. as euery one will easily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. There are also foure Doctours of Physicke inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in ordinarie, with sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geōs
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:98424:106"/> to the number of twelue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="article">
               <head>Of the number and qualitie of those who tend the sicke <hi>ARTICLE XXX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL these Halls, and offices, and all these multitudes of sicke and lame creatures, are looked to, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and prouided for, by the painfull ād perpetual labours of about 100. vertuous Nuuns of S. Augustines order (who make their solemne professiō of the three vowes of pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, chastitie, and obedience, in the presence of the Deane and Canons of our Blessed
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:98424:107"/> Lady, who haue all spirituall and temporall iurisdiction in this place). These fewe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious virgines (fewe, I say, compared to the vast num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the sicke) freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing their owne libertie, and all hopes of wordly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, to become the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the most poore and despicable seruants of God: that I may not say, their slaues, since a more abiect and slauish life can hardly be deuised. Whence Boterays, an ancient Poete, admiring the charitie, and constancie of the said Religious women who serue the sicke amidst so much filth and infection, expresses himselfe in foure latine verses to this effect.</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="213" facs="tcp:98424:107"/>
                  <l>They make themselues the slaues of sicke and lame,</l>
                  <l>To dresse the loathsome sores, we scarce dare name.</l>
                  <l>Their baulme is goare; their ciuet festered wounds;</l>
                  <l>Hence th'odour of their vertue mere abounds.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But what doe these good religious performe in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, or rather what disgust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full drudgeries, abiections, and humiliations are they not lyable to? They washe all the clothes, of those multitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of nastie, goarie, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and euen, too often, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent people. I haue some tymes bene a spectatour of the painfull labours of those poore maydes in the most ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous cold of winter, if not
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:98424:108"/> with edification, certainly not without confusion to my selfe and others, to see them striue to purchace the same heauen we all pretend to, at so deare a rate, while we are confident to buy it for a songe At so deare a rate, I say, spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king according to flesh and bloode, though otherwise it beares noe proportion to that ineffable, eternall, waight of glorie we all ayme at. Truth out of the Apostles mouth, puts is out of doubt, <hi>the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,</hi> afflictions, or sufferances <hi>of this tyme, are not condigne,</hi> or any way comparable, to the greatnesse of <hi>the future glorie which shall be reuealed in vs.</hi> Thence they stand in the riuer all the day longe in great
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:98424:108"/> stiffe bootes, not vnlike to those of fisher men, be it frost, or snow, or blowe what wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will, they are hard at it, with their beetles in their hands, being many tymes all garnished round about their habites with isheakles, the rude winters cristalls, or riuer diamants. To witt they haue some thousands of sheetes and shirts to washe, such (which I leaue to euery ones imagination) as come from the bedds, ād backes of those poore, sicke, wounded and dying wretches. Certainly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the vnction of the holie spirit could euer swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or euen render tolerable, such abiecte and loathsome imployments.</p>
               <pb n="216" facs="tcp:98424:109"/>
               <p>Further they must euery one in their turnes serue them with their meate, deinke, and all thinges necessarie. They must turne and winde them in their bedds, make the same, dresse their scabbs, and wounds &amp;c. watche them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midst the gastly horrour of the night, where death is do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering in the Hall round about them: finally assiste them dying in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, winde their deade bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, and send them to their graues.</p>
               <p>This is truly so admirable, as it would hardly be thought credible, were it not euery day obuious to the eyes of all commers: and more admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble would it yet appeare, were it
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:98424:109"/> not onely beheld in grosse, but looked into in particular. For let vs make computation of the numbers of the assis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants and the assisted, and we shall discouer a strange dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion. The assistātes are one hūdred onely, the assisted 2000. (now more, now fewer, as we haue seene aboue) now 100. compared to 2000. is twentie to one, so that euery Nun has twentie to her parte. Which I presume will be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a sufficient burden by all men who well considere it. One Garde or keeper (as we find by experience) has her hands full to tend and watche one sicke person, especially if for any longe tyme: what an oppressing burden hath one
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:98424:110"/> nun being charged with the care of twentie, not for a smale tyme, not by spirts, and at her owne choyce and pleasure, but at all tymes, by obligation of a vowe as longe as life lasts? Certainly one might truly affirme of those good soules, that they suffer a burden Aetna grauius, did they not experience in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues what their holy father assures them, that they who loue, suffer indeede, the same thinges, but they are not bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>densome to the Leuer, <hi>prae a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more non sentiunt</hi> loue lets them not feele it, which truth all beholders may reade in their faces: for neuer was bride more gay and cheerefull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midst her parents vpon her
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:98424:110"/> mariage day, then they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare amidst their beggars euery day: so that I hope I may not improperly applye (by way of participation) that of the canticles which is addressed to the whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike church, to this illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious parte of it: <hi>multae filiae congregauerunt diuitias, many charitable maydes,</hi> and men of Paris, <hi>haue heaped riches togei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> some by one charitable inuention, some by another, but you haue outstripte them all, by the huge vnlimited amplitude of your charitie, which may seeme, at once, to driue the whole commerce or trading of all the workes of mercy corporall and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, with the whole world,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:98424:111"/> without exception. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with S. Athanasius that if holy Virgines be a certaine marke of the true Church, since none but a virgine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brings out virgins, you more and more confirme the same truth, since to your vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitie, which is truly Angel-like, you ioyne charitie which is the God-like vertue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, yea God himselfe. <hi>Deus est charitas,</hi> which by your holy practises appeares to be putt as absolutly in her raigne, as the condition of this mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable life may permitt.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Liue euer blest, deare mayds, adorne your state</l>
                  <l>And pious sexe, and plac't at highest rate.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>One would haue thought,
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:98424:111"/> after the obseruing of all that hath bene said of this vaste place, that pietie had noe more to haue proiected in relation to it, yet some zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous soule, conceiued that it was not enough, to releeue poore people in their sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and to send them home, being prittie well recouered to make place for others, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the necessitie of the place, vnlesse their chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie prouided further, for their future well beeing, and reesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishmēt in their accustomed strength and vigour; relapses being frequently found more dangerous then the sicknesse it selfe. Here vpon it was, that those cōsiderate persons tooke a house not farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant,
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:98424:112"/> where those new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualescents haue libertie, to passe a longer tyme, in that fresher ayre, and so wholie to confirme their strength.</p>
               <p>The good sisters of the Hostel-Dieu haue yet two houses more which depende vpon their charitable assistāce; to witt S. Lowises in S. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances suburbes, a most spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, magnificent, and truly king like building, whose Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesticall aspect speakes the greatnesse of the royall Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, Henry the greate: and an other, called <hi>la Santé,</hi> a litle distant from S. Marceaux su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs. And they are both alloted to the releife of poore people who may chance to be afflicted with the plague, whō
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:98424:112"/> these goode soules haue the heroicall charitie to tend. In their ordinarie imploy, in the Hostel-Dieu, they freely giue themselues ouer to the most abiect and slauish life imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. But in this, they sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vp themselues to the most dismale death possible, So that they putt the highest rate vpon their charitie, that man is capable of: as is made good by our sauiour himselfe noe man hath a greater cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie then to giue his life for his friends. Liue they happie for euen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="article">
               <pb n="224" facs="tcp:98424:113"/>
               <head>Of the Hospitall called our Ladys of the Incurables. <hi>ARTICLE XXXI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HERE I might well haue putt a periode to this smale worke, but industrious charitie has yet further to goe, and more to prouide for: if she cannot find a fitt and setled place for the poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curables in all the greate va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of Hospitalls yet foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, she will haue one foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on sett purpose for them alone; where if she cannot cure their desperate deseases, she will, at least, solace them in their continuing afflictiōs.
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:98424:113"/> And this blessed office of christianitie, is performed with so much sweetnesse, and affectionate care in this place, that those poore desolate creatures, obseruing, that they suffer not alone, but that their brethren in Christ, beare a part of their burden with them, by compassion; they seeme to be halfe cured.</p>
               <p>The illustrious person, who first inuented and founded this heauenlie habitation, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by the bountifull li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralities of his pious Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie Lowis the XIII. who freed them not onely of all duties belōging to the crowne as <hi>los &amp; vents, maine morts &amp;c.</hi> but also gaue them his rightes of <hi>entrees of wine &amp;c</hi> togeither
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:98424:114"/> with a generall <hi>exemption from all subsidies and impositions &amp;c.</hi> By his letters patentes of Aprill 1637. This illustrious Patron, I say, did so litle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte to feede of the emptie huskes of worldly reputation that he caused his name not to be putt in the kinges let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of establishement. Yet to Gods honour, his, and his noble families, I shall not feare to offend, if I publish to the world, that it was the most religious and Eminent Cardinall <hi>de Rushfaucaud,</hi> who liued, beyond the ordinarie course of nature, to see a good parte of his designe on foote. To which he contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bountifully. To witt he endowed the place with, a
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:98424:114"/> yearly rent <hi>in perpetuū</hi> of three thousand and sixe hundred frankes, or three hundred and sixtie pistolls: and layd downe where with to build a faire church, and two Halls, in the yeare 1637.</p>
               <p>The place fixed vpon for this most agreeable worke, was in S. Germins suburbs. In a most healthfull and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious aire; consisting of noe lesse then ten akres of ground in one faire peece. There the vaste charitie of Paris finds a large field to dilate it selfe vpon. And in verie deede, it seemes it will meete with worke enough for a longe tyme; since, as I am told, the designe is to build eight or ten faire large Halls, all
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:98424:115"/> to be furnished with bedds, as we see at presente, with comlie white fustian courtins with each one a strawe bedd, a feather bedd, and a good quilte; togeither with an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar to euery Hall, where those impotent people may heare Masse in their bedds. Of all these designed Halls, there are, as yet, onely foure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. And yet the iudicious beholder of the statelinesse, and soliditie, of what is alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adie compleated, will easilie iudge it was not compassed for a litle. <hi>Sed charitas omnia sperat.</hi> And the excellent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministratours of the place, are yearly improuing the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues; as well by common cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, which by their singular
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:98424:115"/> industrie and dexteritie, they procure, as by the addition of their owne meanes; some of them paying 1500. liures french or 150. pistolls for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and his man <hi>per annum,</hi> and freely contributing as much more yearelie out of pure charitie; besides 3000. l. which he gaue the first yeare to plainte and beautifie the garden. So farre are those holy men from raysing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues a fortune out of their great places, that they doe not take a competent, and most iust liuely-hoode for their continuall cares and pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but euen pay for it, fiue tymes ouer. So that their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely charitable, and successe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full labours, togeither with
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:98424:116"/> their owne liberalities, high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their hopes to such a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that they confidently propose to themselues, to extende that pious founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which was first made for a douzen onely (sixe men, and sive women) to foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Nor will it be much to be doubted of (if God grant life to those admirable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisours, in whose manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the place now florishes) since by their care, liberalitie and prosperous endeuours, they haue abreadie, in a fewe yeares, multiplied twelue to 160. which are imployed at present. If the rest be once accomplished, it may iustly be stiled the <hi>non such of France,</hi> and the world, for wholsome
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:98424:116"/> aire; magnificent Halls; sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular order; good diete; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable treatement, in all thinges behooffull for body and soule.</p>
               <p>And indeede Gods bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings haue abreadie so visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly appeared vpon this holy foundation, that since the yeare 1637. as aboue, till this present yeare 1666. it is aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the charities of Paris, in point of buildings, to the value of 500. thousand french liures; and as much more in foundatiō of beddes; making in all, a french milliō, besides sixtie thousand liures in annuall reuenues.</p>
               <p>That parte which relates to the bodily care of the incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables, and the continuall
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:98424:117"/> assistances which are necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for those poore creatures which are incapable, in the least to helpe themselues, is performed by good young men (as to the poore men), who out of deuotion subiect themselues to that abiecte im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployement, taking a reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable consideration for that holy and hard seruice: and as to the women, there are modest secular maydes, who complie with the like good offices, with much religion, sweetnesse and compassion.</p>
               <p>The other dutie which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes their soules, is aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly discharged, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall sollicitudes of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of most pious preists, who liue in the place, to be readie vpon euery call, and
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:98424:117"/> who are so absolutly free from all selfe-interest, that they powre out their owne sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, in that Christian ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, in lieu of gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geither any riches therby.</p>
               <p>Witnesse Mr despond the Vicar who hath the cheife charge of the spiritualitie of the place, who out of his owne patrimonie (in a fewe yeares that he has liued there) hath giuen the house aboue 12. thousand liures; with inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to leaue his faire and well choysen librarie, which is worth 10. thousand more for the vse therof. So that <hi>aurt sacra fames</hi> which hath so ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute a raigne in the world, among them is turned, to a spirituall prodigalitie, and
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:98424:118"/> holy strife to outuie each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In a word, the beautifull contriuance of the whole buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge; the maiestie of the Halls (which might rather seeme to be <hi>Louures,</hi> then lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings fore poore distressed people) the excellencie of the situation, and the odour of the admirable charitie pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised therin, delightfully allure persons of great worth and honour, to reside there, as Abbots Counsellours &amp;c. who after they haue giuen ample testimonies of their abilities, in profitably seruing the publike the best of their yeares, know to make a holy retreate, and to sacrifice vp the honorable rest of what they sometymes were, to
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:98424:118"/> God alone, in that deuoute sanctuarie, where they build themselues noble quarters, which are looked vpon as <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationes inter viuos,</hi> during their liues, to be left to the Hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall, as monuments of their pietie, after their deathes. Most worthily may be added to these, that most famous Bishope of Bellay, that louer of the poore and pouertie, which he truly practised: for tho he did not actually liue with them, yet did his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and approbation, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes accompaignie them, his ambition, as he oft said, neuer going higher, then to be reputed a poore Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of that holy familie. Hence he left them what he
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:98424:119"/> had, and the relikes of what he had bene, to be interred in their Church. <hi>Requiescat in pace</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="article">
               <head>Of diuers other charities which I cannot so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el particularise. <hi>ARTICLE XXXII</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF here I make an end, it is not for want of matter further to inlarge my selfe, but for want of tyme and health to informe my selfe of the particulars: for I am not ignorant, that there are many other excellent workes of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie exercised in Paris. As in that Hospitall of the Racquett in the Suburbs of S. Antonies which depends vpon another in the towne, behind the place
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:98424:119"/> royall: gouerned by a cōpanie of good nuns of S. Augusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes order, who receiue a many good burgesses, in their infirmities and incommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and treate them with much charitie and goodnesse, affording thē hansome bedds, good diet, and all thinges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie.</p>
               <p>I know there are other two houses, effects of the late cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of Paris. The one for men, the other for women newly conuerted. The first in S. Victors suburbs: the other neere S. Eustaches. They are taken in, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned <hi>gratis</hi> for three mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes space at least, to be throughly instructed, and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly setled in the truth.</p>
               <pb n="238" facs="tcp:98424:120"/>
               <p>I remember also that aboue 20. yeares agoe, there came a good Lady (from Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux as I am told) to Paris, called Madame l'Estang, with a harte as full of good will to doe workes of common cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as hands emptie of meanes to performe it. Yet God hath so blessed her pious endeuours among the Good people of Paris, that she has procured subsistance for 250. poore young maydes, (which her care hath gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geither) who by her graue prudence, are modestly and christianly bredd, and carre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully kept out of harmes way, to which that sexe, and those greene yeares, are but too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident.</p>
               <pb n="239" facs="tcp:98424:120"/>
               <p>All Paris knowes, and sees daylie, multitudes of girles, taught (for meere charitie) to serue God, to reade, to write, to worke diuers kinds of workes, wherby they are inabled to become good hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiues at home, or to gaine their liuelyhood among the marchands. And this as well at religious houses, especially the visulaines, whose proper profession it is, as in diuers particular cōgregatiōs (which are common all ouer Paris) where good widdowes, and ancient matrons, deuote thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to that pious care.</p>
               <p>To conclude, poore distres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed people of the generall Hospitall, the otherwise de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted gallie-slaues, and the
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:98424:121"/> desolate prisoners, often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience the comfortable vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sites of the noblest Ladyes of Paris, who solace the first with their affabilitie and pious discourse, and, often tymes, deliuer the latter, by paying the summe for which they were imprisoned. These thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, I beleeue, will be farre from being paralled by the protestāts practises. Howbeit there are yet others that much further outspeake thē, which for breuities sake I will onely point at.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="article">
               <head>Obseruations to be made of other great workes of pietie. <hi>ARTICLE XXIX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOME of the greatest ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of true pietie,
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:98424:121"/> zeale and religion, especially towards God, I haue not yet touched. For what indeede doth antiquitie deliuer vs, which speakes more honour to God, and the noble foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, then the erection of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples dedicated to his name; those royall and permanent monumēts of primitiue zeale, whose venerable old lookes decrye prophane noueltie, and prescribe against it, with Tertulians <hi>prior possideo, olim possideo: I possesse first, I possesse of old.</hi> Whose verie exteriour forme (which is ordinarily found the same all christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome about) preaches a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified God, in a silent lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guadge, which heresie could neuer refute, saue onely by
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:98424:122"/> the new way of pulling them downe.</p>
               <p>Hence it was, that the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest of kinges, Salomon: the greatest of Emperours, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine the great: the Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relesse Empresse his mother, Helena; and Edgar the most religious of our kinges (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the three last are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable ornaments of our <hi>olim</hi> holy Hand) commended the memorie of their most renowmed pietie (to omitte millions of others) in pointe of building Temples, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall posteritie.</p>
               <p>In this point what glorious aduantages could I not meete with, should I prosequute it to the full: How rare and leane fruites hath England
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:98424:122"/> seene in this kind, in 100. yeares and vpwards, that is, euer since the young birth of protestancie? while the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike pietie of Paris, in thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares space, hath produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at least 40. considerable churches and chapells (with faire Monasteries to the most of them) which I am able to giue a catalogue of, without stirring my foote out of my studie, to inquire them out.</p>
               <p>And firsts in S. Iames his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs are these which follow.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Institution of the Oratoire.</item>
                  <item>2. Port-Royall.</item>
                  <item>3. Vall de Grace.</item>
                  <item>4. The Fuliantines.</item>
                  <item>5. The Vrselines.</item>
                  <item>6. The Visitation.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="244" facs="tcp:98424:123"/>
                  <head>In Germains suburbs.</head>
                  <item>7. Caluaire.</item>
                  <item>8. The Carmes.</item>
                  <item>9. The Iesuits No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiship.</item>
                  <item>10. The Misericorde</item>
                  <item>11. The dixe Vertue</item>
                  <item>12. Chasse Midy</item>
                  <item>12. The Incurables</item>
                  <item>14. Belchace.</item>
                  <item>15. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acobins</item>
                  <item>16. The Petits Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustins.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>In S. Mercels suburbs.</head>
                  <item>17. The Misericorde</item>
                  <item>18. The Pitié.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>In the Vniuersitie</head>
                  <item>19. S. Stephens reedified a nev</item>
                  <item>20. The Sorbon.</item>
                  <item>21. Clarmont</item>
                  <item>22. S. Nicolas, nov makeing all a new.</item>
                  <item>23. Bon Enfans.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>In the Isle de Nostre-Dame.</head>
                  <item>24. S. Lovis.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>In the Isle de Palais.</head>
                  <item>25. The Bernabits.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>In S. Honories Suburbs.</head>
                  <item>26. Villeuesque.</item>
                  <item>27. Conception</item>
                  <item>28. The Assumption.</item>
                  <item>29. The Feulliens.</item>
                  <item>30. S. ROCK.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="245" facs="tcp:98424:123"/>
                  <head>In the towne it selfe.</head>
                  <item>31. The Oratorians</item>
                  <item>32. The litle Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustins.</item>
                  <item>33. Filles de S Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas.</item>
                  <item>34. The Carmeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</item>
                  <item>35. S. Eustace ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified.</item>
                  <item>36. The Carmelites Rue Chapon.</item>
                  <item>37. The Iesuites S. Antoine.</item>
                  <item>38. The Visitation S. Antoine</item>
                  <item>39. The Minimes</item>
                  <item>40. The Carmes Mitigez.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And note by the way, that there are siue or sixe of the foresaid churches, in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar that of <hi>Val de Grace,</hi> the monument of a most pious queene, and the worldes Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon: that of Sorbon, the worke of the vnparelled Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Richelisu. And that of the Iesuites in S. Antonies streete, wherof the first (which is iudged to haue cost some millions) is able to pay fore more churches (to speake sparingly) thē all England has
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:98424:124"/> built since the fall of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like religion. A royall munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence! worthy of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the wife, the sister, the mother of a kinge: a Deoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus or child of miracle: and grand-mother of a kingly issue. And yet that which out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakes all, is that this vast ād holily profuse liberalitie, in this kind, hindered her not <hi>bountifully to opē her hād to the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and to stretche out her palmes to the poore,</hi> so that she was obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued (by faithfull and knowing persons) annually to cōtribute twētie, or twentie two thousād pistolls, with her owne royall hands, to the poore and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitous, those liuing, and better Temples of God. And as to the rest, wheras I in my chamber, without further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisition,
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:98424:124"/> counte but vpon fortie, others better able to stirre abroade, and so better versed in the towne, make noe difficultie to affirme, that there are many more, which I easily beleeue. How soeuer it may be, as to the iust num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the number I haue spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified is most certainly true, and ministers most iust occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to me, to say to your church, what S. Augustine said to the Donatists, <hi>produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite aliquid simile,</hi> produce some thing like to this, for the proofe of your pietie.</p>
               <p>Now if thus much be said for the pietie which appeares in the walls, what might not iustly be said, for the religious liues of the heauenlie inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants?
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:98424:125"/> who endeuouring to followe Christs counsell (which certainlie was not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by wisdome it selfe to fall fruitlesse to the ground; to be neglected by all men, to be imitated by none) of a more perfect way of life then the meere keeping of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandementes, went and sold, or abandonned, all that they had, and all that they could hope for, in this poore world to become therby the poore of Christ, and tooke vp their Crosse, that is, a penitentiall life; gaue it to the poore, and followed him, by imitating his diuine chastitie, pouertie and obedience, as farre forth as by his grace, they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable therof. Who haue but
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:98424:125"/> one harte, and one soule in our Lord: one comon habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, one purse, one pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie: and liue at such a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance from any reall proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that those colde wordes <hi>meum &amp; tuum,</hi> myne and thyne (the sourse of all dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sension) are banished out of their societie. Whose whole application, as well by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession as practise, is to God and godly studies: whose ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise is to pray, and singe heauenly Psalmes, Hymnes, and cāticles before the throne of God day and night: in a worde, whose conuersation is intirely in Heauen. Hence Monasticall persons are sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by S. Cyprian, the most illustrious parte of the church of God: by S. Ambrose an
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:98424:126"/> imitation in earth of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells in heauen: and S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine, breaten backe by the glorious luster of their Angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall practises, professeth, that hauing a mynde to prayse them, he dare not vndertake it, because expression, saith he, would fayle him. The like fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling might I much more iustly feare, should I aduenture to prayse (whom, in passing by, I onely ayme to point at) those infinite numbers of Religious men, and holie virgins, who adorne Paris at this day, with the like sublime pietie and sā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie, as he magnified in his tyme, in the Catholike church when he prouoked the Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies <hi>to reprehend, if they could, those manners, that life, that order, that institute</hi> (which he
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:98424:126"/> had described in his booke <hi>de moribus Eeclesiae Catholicae)</hi> and not still to goe on in vainely boasting of our chaffe, to blind men, who are not capable to iudge of light. With him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for I will conclude with you, humbly beseeching you for Gods loue, not to giue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eare to your mens slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Catholi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e church in catching an occasion, by the reprehension of their mā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, whom she also condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and continually striues to correct, as being the faultes of naughtie childrē. &amp; yet if they persiste in their wichedesse, or euen adde more greeuous faults to the former, they are suffered not withstanding to remayne in our Lords field,
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:98424:127"/> and to growe vp with the good seede, according to Christs or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the gospell: <hi>suffer both to grow vntill the haruest:</hi> but a tyme will come, that the cockle shall be separated, and the pure wheate shall be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from the chaffe. In the interim, deare Sr, I leaue your equitie to iudge, <hi>whether it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare not a kind of impudence</hi> (as saith S. August) <hi>in your men, to seeke,</hi> and as it were, to exacte, <hi>that perfection in our looser mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> and euen in the chaffe of our Church <hi>(therby to seduce the ignorant) when they, the while, shew not, in the least measure,</hi> the same perfection, in theirs, to those whom they seduce.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98424:127"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>